<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The first centvry of scandalous, malignant priests, made and admitted into benefices by the prelates, in whose hands the ordination of ministers and government of the church hath been. Or, A narration of the causes for which the Parliament hath ordered the sequestration of the benefices of severall ministers complained of before them, for vitiousnesse of life, errors in doctrine, contrary to the articles of our religion, and for practising and pressing superstitious innovations against law, and for malignancy against the Parliament. It is ordered this seventeenth day of November, 1643. by the Committee of the House of Commons in Parliament concerning printing, that this booke intituled, [The first century of scandalous, malignant priests, &amp;c.] be printed by George Miller.</title>
            <author>White, John, 1590-1645.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 136 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96350</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1777</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E76_21</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19192</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860603</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860603</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112727</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96350)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112727)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 13:E76[21])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The first centvry of scandalous, malignant priests, made and admitted into benefices by the prelates, in whose hands the ordination of ministers and government of the church hath been. Or, A narration of the causes for which the Parliament hath ordered the sequestration of the benefices of severall ministers complained of before them, for vitiousnesse of life, errors in doctrine, contrary to the articles of our religion, and for practising and pressing superstitious innovations against law, and for malignancy against the Parliament. It is ordered this seventeenth day of November, 1643. by the Committee of the House of Commons in Parliament concerning printing, that this booke intituled, [The first century of scandalous, malignant priests, &amp;c.] be printed by George Miller.</title>
                  <author>White, John, 1590-1645.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 51, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Miller, dwelling in the Black-Friers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XLIII.[1643]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John White.  cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nov: 22.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112727:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112727:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FIRST CENTVRY OF Scandalous, Malignant PRIESTS, Made and admitted into Benefices by the PRELATES, in whoſe hands the Ordination of Miniſters and government of the Church hath been. <hi>OR,</hi> A Narration of the Cauſes for which the <hi>PARLIAMENT hath Ordered the</hi> Sequeſtration of the Benefices of ſeverall Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters complained of before them, for vitiouſneſſe of Life, errors in Doctrine, contrary to the Articles of our Religion, and for practiſing and preſſing <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious Innovations againſt Law, and</hi> for Malignancy againſt the <hi>PARLIAMENT.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="license">
                  <body>
                     <p>IT is Ordered this ſeventeenth day of <hi>November,</hi> 1643. by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of the Houſe of Commons in Parliament concerning Printing, that this Booke Intituled, [<hi>The firſt Century of Scandalous, Malignant Prieſts,</hi> &amp;c.] be printed by <hi>George Miller.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>JOHN WHITE.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>George Miller,</hi> dwelling in the <hi>Black-Friers,</hi> M.DC.XLIII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:112727:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:112727:2"/>
            <head>To the <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His enſuing ſummary Declaration, of the Grounds and Cauſes, whereupon this Parliament hath proceeded againſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Miniſters, to ſequeſter their Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices from them, and to place in their roomes, godly, learned, orthodox Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, diligent Preachers of the Word of God, may ſerve thee for many excellent parpoſes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, To open thine eyes and clearely convince and ſatisfie thee, that the Parliament had good, and very great cauſe from hence, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong many other things, to declare and reſolve, that the preſent Church Governement by Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, their Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, Commiſſaries, Deanes, Arch-deacons, and other Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Officers, depending upon the Hierarchie, is evill and justly Offenſive and burdenſome to the Kingdome, a great Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment to Reformation and growth of Religion, and very pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiciall to the State and Government of this Kingdome, and therefore to be taken away
<note n="a" place="margin">See the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amble of the bill for the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, and of the Ordinance by which they ſit.</note>: They have beene by our Lawes entruſted with the Care and Proviſion for the ſoules of the King and Subjects, to heed, feed and watch over them
<note n="b" place="margin">Acts 20.28. 1 Pet. 5.2. Heb. 13.17.</note>: And to attend upon the great Embaſſie they pretend unto, to pray and beſeech them <hi>to be reconciled unto God</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.20.</note>: and to preach
<pb facs="tcp:112727:3"/>and to cauſe to be preached by able and faithfull men
<note n="d" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.2.</note>: The <hi>Word of God in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">2 Tim. 4 2.</note>: They have not onely neglected their Perſonall Execution of this weighty truſt, but alſo have generally and moſtly committed the ſame to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons illiterate and inſufficient, <hi>dumbe Doggs,</hi> as the Scripture calls them
<note n="f" place="margin">Iſa. 56.10.</note>, <hi>that cannot barke,</hi> againſt whom God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted for their ignorance
<note n="g" place="margin">Hoſ. 4.6.</note>, and to men ſwallowed up with <hi>Wine and ſtrong drinke, whoſe Tables are full of vomit and filthineſſe
<note n="h" place="margin">Iſai. 28.7.8. <hi>Quorum eſſ. et vivere eſt eſſe &amp; bibere.</hi>
                  </note>: Whoremongers and Adulterers, who as fed Horſes neigh after their Neighbours Wives
<note n="i" place="margin">Jer. 5.8.</note>: Buggerers that change the naturall uſe into that which is againſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 1.26.</note>. And to others ſcandalous of corrupt mindes, and ill affected to the Peace and Safety of the Kingdome, men unfit to preach to, or live among Chriſtians, their wickedneſſe being ſo great, as that they are condemned by Heathens: And hereby they have taken the high-way to deſtroy the ſouls committed to them, and to drown them in Perdition. The evill life of a Miniſter, being like the rods, which <hi>Jacob</hi> spread before the Sheepe
<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Precepts are</hi> iter longum. <hi>Examples</hi> iter breve.</note>, the people write after his copie with eaſe and confidence. Sinnes are reputed, as none, or as veniall, which receive Patronage from the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters Example
<note n="n" place="margin">Hae hominum faces non Dei miniſtri, ſed Satanae ſatelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, non Chriſti ſeblatores, ſed Antichriſte ſucceſsores.</note>. And though ſome few of theſe Church Governors, have been men that have otherwiſe expreſſed in the courſe of their lives a true feare of God, yet by a ſtrange Influence of the Divine Curſe upon their Offices, branches of the Hierarchy of <hi>Rome,</hi> plants not planted by our heavenly Father, theſe as well as the reſt, have unhappily laid hands ſuddenly upon many, and preferred divers wicked and unworthy, by partiality
<note n="o" place="margin">1 Tim. 5.2.</note>, to marry and put off their hands a Daughter, a Kinſwoman, and upon other bie and baſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects, without regard of the good of the ſoules of them, over whom they were ſet. And in this Booke, thou ſhalt have an Aſſay of the Gall and Worme-wood of the <hi>Epiſcopall Governement,</hi> taken out of <hi>London</hi> the <hi>Metropolis,</hi> and of the Counties adjacent, that when thou ſeeſt what Vermine crawles upon, and devoures the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall and vitall parts, thou maiſt reflect with a mournefull heart up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the more miſerable condition of <hi>Wales,</hi> and of the <hi>North,</hi> the more remote parts of this Kingdome, where upon ſcrutiny will be eaſily found, many for one as vile and abhominable as theſe. And if thou wouldost have the people periſh for want of viſion or impoyſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:112727:3"/>with the deſtructive Errours of <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Arminianiſme,</hi> and the Land yet more defiled with curſing, ſwearing, drunkenneſſe; whoredome, ſodomie, then put thy ſhoulders ſtill to the ſupport of the ſaid Church-Government and Governours, but if thou be better minded (as in Charitie I hope thou art) then joyne heart and hand with the Parliament, to purge out ſuch Popiſh dreggs, and together with them, pray for and endeavour a through Reformation, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Thou maiſt by peruſall of this booke clearly ſee what manner of perſons thoſe Cleargie-men be, that favour the preſent courſe of his Majeſtie againſt his Parliament and people, and diſlike and maligne the wayes of the Parliament, they will appeare unto thee to be ſuch as cannot endure the purity, power and ſtrictneſſe of the true Religion, that hate Reformation, and to be brought in their hearts, Religion and lives to the holy Word of God, that ſeeks themſelves and not the things of Jeſus Christ, that are given over to vile affections, to ſuperſtition, ambition, perſecutions, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, malignity and all wickednes, and knowing the judgement of God and what they deſerve that commit ſuch things, yet not only doe the ſame, but <hi>have pleaſure in them that doe them</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 1.28, 29 32.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Thou maieſt hereby diſcerne one principall ground and cauſe of the generall ignorance and debauchery of the Gentry and people of this Kingdome. <hi>Like Prieſt, like people
<note n="b" place="margin">Hoſ. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>: They cauſe the people to erre by their lyes and by their lightneſſe
<note n="c" place="margin">Jer. 23.31.</note>: They are a ſnare on</hi> Miſpah, <hi>and a net ſpread upon</hi> Tabor
<note n="d" place="margin">Hoſ. 5.1.</note>. <hi>They have wreſted and broken the law of the Lord, defiled his holy things, hid their eyes from his Sabbaths, polluted his Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Ezek. 22.26.</note>, and ſeduced the people to the ſame wickedneſſe, <hi>dawbing with untempered Morter</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Ezek. 13.10.</note> Theſe Prophets propheſie falſly, the Biſhops beare rule by their means, and the people love to have it ſo
<note n="g" place="margin">Jer. 5.31.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Behold with admiration, and acknowledge with love and thankefulneſſe the tranſcendent mercie of the Lord, to his poore people among us, that whereas he hath infinite juſt cauſe to deſtroy theſe Prieſts and people together, cloath them with deſolation, and doe unto them after their waies, and judge them according to their deſert
<note n="h" place="margin">Ezek. 7.27.</note>. He is graciouſly pleaſed to ſtirre up a spirit of zeale and judgement in the Parliament to deliver the people from the mouthes of theſe Shepheards, that feed not the flocke, but kill them that are
<pb facs="tcp:112727:4"/>fed, eate the fat, and cloath themſelves with the wool
<note n="l" place="margin">Ez k. 34.3, 10.</note>: and to ſet true ſhepheards over them, to ſeeke that which was loſt, and bring againe that which was driven away, to bind them that were broken, and ſtrengthen them that were ſick, and to feed them all, with know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and underſtanding; and to feed with judgment the wicked ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards that before with force and cruelty ruled over them
<note n="k" place="margin">Eze. 34.15, 16.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fiftly,</hi> Behold with comfort and aſſured expectation of good from Heaven, that as the Lord hath manifested his gracious purpoſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme his Church in this Land, and ſet up the Kingdome of Christ among us, in the purity of Doctrine and Diſcipline, and hath for that purpoſe called this Parliament, fixed it, ſet it upon that worke, and maintained it therein, and in all theſe hath manifeſted his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate hand and finger, in ſtupendious works of Divine provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, opening obſtructions, working that himſelfe which his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants could not, making the very enemies of Reformation meanes to further it; diſcovering and preventing the horrid, hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, treacherous plots of his and our enemies, turning the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells of <hi>Achitophell</hi> into folly, diſcovering the rotten hearts of them, that ſaid they were for the Cauſe of God, but are found ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; and holding up the hearts of his faithfull ones in the middeſt of, and againſt all diſcouragements. So the Lord is pleaſed to carry on his great worke of Reformation, in the very face and in aispight of all oppoſitions and dangers, that it gaines ground and creepes on every day. Theſe Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> ſonnes of <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liall,</hi> that know not the Lord, whoſe ſinne is very great before God, in making multitudes abhorre the Offerings of the Lord
<note n="a" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.12, 17.</note>, are taken away and removed as filthy rubbiſh from the houſe of God. The <hi>Antinomians</hi> that destroy the Law, as neither di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory nor obligatory of a Chriſtian to duty: and teach, that God ſees not, is not angry with, will not correct, requires not ſorrow for, nor repentance of the groſſeſt ſinnes that are commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſuch as beleeve they be in Chriſt; and that the elect are actually juſtified as ſoone as borne, though they have not faith in forty yeares after, and many ſuch abſurdities and barbariſmes in Divinity, are queſtioned and in a good way to be ſuppreſſed, and the Doctrine of our Church in a great part cleared from all asperſions and miſconſtructions. <hi>This is the Lords doing, and it is marvellous in our eyes.</hi> And certainely theſe works of
<pb facs="tcp:112727:4"/>God, are ſo many earneſt-pence unto us, as the firſt fruits to the harveſt, that God will in his own way and time perfect his ſaid worke of a through Reformation, and bring forth and lay the head and top<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone thereof, that we and our postority ſhall rejoyce and cry <hi>grace grace unto it</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Zech. 4.7.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Whereas in ſeverall Proclamations, Declarations and Pamphlets ſet forth in his Majeſties name, and otherwiſe ſent us from <hi>Oxford,</hi> the Parliament hath been exceedingly reproached and condemned (as in truth they have been for all the good they have done for the Kingdome) for Sequeſtring the Livings of Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Divines (as they ſtile them) thou mayeſt by a ſerious peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of this Booke, cleerely ſee what Divines the Authours and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhers of the ſaid Pamphlets doe ſo reverence and eſteeme; And from thence obſerve of what ſpirit theſe men are that ſide with, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, pleade for, and receive unto them ſuch Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> of <hi>Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> of <hi>Priapus;</hi> Doth not their affection unto, and high esteeme of ſuch uncleane beaſts, abundantly evince, that they ſerve and proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute themſelves unto the ſame dung-hill Idols and filthy luſts, and that they are all of the ſame Father? And note further, that theſe Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellers not only ſpeake evill of Dignities, but alſo of thoſe things that they know not
<note n="c" place="margin">Jude 8.10.</note>, they Cenſure the Supreame Court of Judicature, themſelves being Delinquents, deferving the ſevereſt judgement, and that without hearing them, or informing themſelves of what they have done, notwithſtanding all their acts and proceedings lie fairely of record in their Journall bookes, obvious to every man that deſires to underſtand the ſame. And that the Parliament may appeare juſt in their doings, and the mouth of iniquity may be ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, this Narrative of the crimes,
<note n="*" place="margin">The groſſeſt faults ſtand proved by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny witneſſes, ſeldome leſſe then ſix.</note> and miſdemeanours of thoſe ſons of the earth are here publiſhed, that all the world may ſee, that the tongues of theſe that ſpeake evill of the Parliament, are ſet on fire of Hell, and lift up againſt Heaven, and that they hide themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der falſehood, and make lies their refuge.</p>
            <p>And let not the Learning of ſome few of theſe men (for w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> if they had any grace to uſe it well, they were conſiderable) move thee to thinke they be hardly dealt with, for learning in a man unſanctified, is but a pearle in a Swines ſnout, <hi>Arrins, Pelagius, Arminius,</hi> all of them learned, but thereby the more ſerviceable to doe miſchiefe in the Church; like <hi>Curio,</hi> who was <hi>facundus</hi> only <hi>ad reipublicae per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niciem.</hi> Learning and knowledge we honour in any, but vitiouſneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:112727:5"/>and lewdneſſe we condemne in all: had ſome of theſe men ſanctity of life as well as light of knowledge, they had been honourable to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and uſefull to ſoules; but their abhorred lusts caſting out of them the guidance of light, it is but justice to caſt them off from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing guides to others: I ſay, Juſtice to them, and withall mercy to the poore people, who at once are ridde of a plague, and enjoy a bleſſing, are freed from ſuch who poiſoned their ſoules, and ſupplied by ſuch as take care to feed and ſave their ſoules
<note n="a" place="margin">None ſucceed theſe ſequeſt. red Prieſts, but ſuch as are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the Aſſembly of Divines.</note>.</p>
            <p>I know well that all we ſay or doe in this particular will be reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by ſome, but good ſervices muſt not therefore be deſerted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe reproached. When the fat Abbies were taken downe in <hi>Henry</hi> the eights time, the Friers cried out that holy Church was destroyed, yet when the draughts and ponds were ſearched, ſo many bones and skulls were found, which aſſured men of practiſes diſtant enough from holineſſe. For my part I ſhall not ceaſe to endeavour and pray for a perfect reformation of the Church, which is the garden wherein God delighteth to walke, and therefore muſt be purged of all ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and noyſome weeds. And doe thou (whoſoever thou art, that fixeſt thine eye on this display) learne by the evills which thou readeſt, to bewaile the greater evills in this ſinfull Land which thou yet doſt not know
<note n="b" place="margin">The follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Centuries will make a more full Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of the wickedneſſes that are among us.</note>: When malice hath ſpoken its worſt and done its utmoſt, then ſhalt thou cleerely underſtand what I daily ſee and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely know, that the great ſervices and paines of the Parliament have no other ſcope but divine glory, the Churches reformation, and the Kingdomes ſafety. Conſider ſadly and ſeriouſly of theſe things, and the Lord give thee and me understanding of theſe times, to know what <hi>Iſraell</hi> ought to doe in the ſame; and let us without feare of the hand of violence, or foote of pride, ſet hand and heart, and ſhoulder and all, to the perfect cleanſing of the houſe of the Lord, and advancing his <hi>Sion</hi> to a perfection of beauty, and ſetting up his Chriſt upon his Throne, to rule over us in all things according to his own mind, and then expect with fulneſſe of aſſurance, that he will speedily make all his enemies his foot-ſtoole, and eaſe himſelfe and us of all his adverſaries. Which is the prayer</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>of him that deſireth to ſpend himſelfe and be ſpent in the ſervice of the King and Kingdome,</hi>
                  <hi>JOHN WHITE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112727:5"/>
            <head>THE FIRST CENTVRY OF Scandalous and Lewde <hi>MINISTERS.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Benefice of <hi>Iohn Wilſon</hi> Vicar of <hi>Arlington</hi> in the County of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he in moſt beaſtly manner, divers times attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to commit buggery with <hi>Nathaniel Browne, Samuel Andrewes</hi> and <hi>Robert Williams</hi> his Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioners, and by perſwaſions and violence, laboured to draw them to that abhominable ſinne, <hi>that</hi> (as he ſhamed not to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe) <hi>they might make up his number eighteene;</hi> and hath profeſſed, <hi>that he made choice to commit that act with man-kind rather then with women, to avoide the ſhame and danger that oft enſueth in begetting Baſtards;</hi> and hath alſo attempted to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Buggery with a Mare, and at Baptizing of a Baſtard child, blaſphemouſly ſaid, openly in the Church, <hi>That our Saviour as he was in the fleſh, was a Bastard;</hi> and uſually preacheth, <hi>That Baptiſme utterly taketh away originall ſinne, and that the ſinnes committed after Baptiſme, are only by imitation, and not by naturall corruption;</hi> and hath in his Sermons, much commended Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in Churches, as good for edification, and <hi>that men ſhould pray with Beades,</hi> and hath openly ſaid, <hi>that the Parliament were Rebels, and endeavoured to ſtarve the King,</hi> and <hi>that whatſoever the King commands, we are all bound to obey, whether it be good or evill;</hi> and hath openly affirmed, <hi>that Buggery is no
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:112727:6"/>ſinne,</hi> and is a uſuall frequenter of Ale-houſes, and a great drinker.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſtipend of <hi>Iohn Aymes</hi> Curate of <hi>Lowis</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtred, for that he is a common drunkard, a common haunter of Ale-houſes, and a common ſwearer; and hath affirmed the Parliament <hi>to be a Round-headed Parliament, and that their heads ſhould be all ſhortly chopt off;</hi> and wiſhed, <hi>that the King might grind them in pieces like a Potters veſsell,</hi> and for above 15. weekes hath altogether deſerted his Cure.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Benefice of <hi>Charles Forbench</hi> Parſon of <hi>Heny</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſsex,</hi> was ſequeſtred, becauſe he is a common ſwearer, oftentimes breaking forth into fearfull Oathes and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precations, and very careleſſe of his paſtorall function, and wholy neglecteth the obſerving of the monethly Faſt, ſetting his men to plow, himſelfe alſo working on thoſe dayes in the fields, and hath affirmed, <hi>that the Earle of</hi> Strafford <hi>was no trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour, and that he was put to death wrongfully by the</hi> Parliament.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Benefice of <hi>Stephen Withers</hi> Parſon of <hi>Kelvedon</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſsex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he hath ſollicited often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the Wife of <hi>Philip Glaſcomb</hi> to commit adultery with him, and divers other women, affirming it <hi>to be no ſinne to lie with them.</hi> And hath not only practiſed Altar-worſhip, but urged his people to receive the Sacrament of the Lords Supper at the railes, and in his Church read the Booke for prophanation of the Sabbath by ſports, and will not ſuffer his people to have above one Sermon on the Lords day, though at their charge; and hath expreſſed great malignity againſt the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. The Benefice of <hi>Emanuel Vty,</hi> Doctor in Divinity, Rector of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Chigwell</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtred, for that he affirmed, <hi>that there hath beene no true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion in</hi> England <hi>theſe forty yeares, and that he loved the Pope with all his heart,</hi> peremptorily maintaining <hi>that whatſoever men of holy Orders ſpeake, they ſpeake by Divine inſpiration, and that if the Devill himſelfe would have holy Orders put on him, he would be inſpired by the holy Ghoſt,</hi> and hath denied the Kings Supremacy,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112727:6"/>and exalted the Power of Biſhops above the Authority of the Prince, affirming them to be the head of the Church; and blaſphemouſly broached, <hi>That the Command of the Arch-biſhop of</hi> Canterbury <hi>was to be equally obeyed with the Word of God,</hi> and hath declaimed againſt the Authority of Parliament, and affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, <hi>That Parliament-men are Mechanicks and illiterate, and have nothing to doe to intermeddle in matters of Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. The Benefice of <hi>Edward Cherry,</hi> Rector of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Much-holland</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he uſually boweth twelve times towards the Eaſt, when he goeth into the Chancell, and his Sermons which were rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly above one a Moneth, moſtly tend to the upholding and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of that and the like ſuperſtitious innovations, and hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to give the Sacrament to thoſe of his Pariſhioners that would not come up to the railes to receive it; and hath taught in his Sermons, <hi>That Baptiſme waſheth away originall ſinne, and that all men may be ſaved if they will, and have free-will thereunto,</hi> and hath been very often drunke; and affirmed, <hi>that a man may more lawfully play, game and drinke in an Ale-houſe on the Sunday, then on any other day;</hi> and hath publiſhed a very ſcandalous Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell againſt the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> Earle of <hi>Warwick,</hi> and Earle of <hi>Holland,</hi> and hath affirmed, <hi>That he never knew any good the Parliament did, unleſſe it were to rob the Country and pick their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and hath deſerted his ſaid Cure for above a yeare laſt paſt, leaving the ſame wholy unſupplied, and is reputed to have beta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken himſelfe to the Army raiſed againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The Benefice of <hi>Thomas Thrall,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of S. <hi>Mary Mount-thaw London,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he hath neither Preached nor Catechized on the Lords day in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, nor ſuffered his Pariſhioners to have any to performe the ſame, though they have deſired it at their own charge; And is a common haunter of Tavernes and Ale-houſes, ſpending much of his time there, and hath been often drunke, and not only read the Booke for ſports on the Sabbath in his Church, but hath ſtirred up his Pariſhioners thereunto, and countenanced
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112727:7"/>them with his preſence at Cudgells and the like other ſports on that day, and ſaid, <hi>that the Houſe of Commons in Parliament was an unjuſt Court;</hi> and doth ordinarily ſweare and curſe, and uſeth ſuperſtitious bowing and cringing to the Communion Table.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The Benefice of <hi>Iohn Gordon,</hi> Rector of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Ockley</hi> in the County of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common haunter of Ale-houſes and Tavernes, ſitting and tipling there, night after night, and hath ſpent the whole Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath there, ſo that no Service nor Sermon was in his Church by reaſon thereof, and is a common drunkard, and hath not preached on any Faſt day ſince it was enjoyned by King and Parliament, and hath publiſhed in his Church, <hi>all thoſe to be Traitours that lent to the Parliament,</hi> and hath deſerted his ſaid Church for about ſix Moneths laſt paſt, and is reported to have been ſeene in the Army of Cavalieres, raiſed againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="9">9. The Benefice of <hi>Lawrence Waſhington,</hi> Rector of <hi>Purleigh</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common frequenter of Ale-houſes, not only himſelfe ſitting daily tip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling there, but alſo incouraging others in that beaſtly vice, and hath been oft drunke, and hath ſaid, <hi>That the Parliament have more Papiſts-belonging to them in their Armies, then the King had about him or in his Army,</hi> and <hi>that the Parliaments Army did more hurt then the Cavaleeres, and that they did none at all;</hi> And hath publiſhed them to be Traitours, that lend to or aſſiſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
            <p n="10">10. The Benefice of <hi>Philip Leigh,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Redburne</hi> in the County of <hi>Hertford,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common drunkard and haunter of Alehouſes, uſually drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king healths, and preſſing others thereunto, a common ſwearer and quarreller, and hath expreſſed much malignancy againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="11">11. The Benefices of <hi>Francis Fothersby</hi> Vicar of S. <hi>Clements</hi> in <hi>Sandwich,</hi> and Parſon of <hi>Lingſteede</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent;</hi> are ſequeſtred, for that he is a common drunkard, and common
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112727:7"/>ſwearer and curſer, and hath expreſſed great malignancy againſt the Parliament, in not only refuſing to contribute to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like defence of, but ſaying, <hi>that they that would not lend the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament money, ſhould be ſent with Ordinances to Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12. The ſtipend of <hi>Daniel Tutivall</hi> Preacher of <hi>Suttons</hi> Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitall in the County of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> commonly called <hi>Charter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he hath been often drunke, and that on the Lords day, and hath taught in his Sermons to the ſaid Houſe, that <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> being before them (meaning two Pictures ſet up in the Chappell) and the Organs behind them (newly alſo ſet up there) <hi>they were a happy people, and what grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter comfort could mortall men have?</hi> and hath wholy neglected the obſervation of the Monethly Faſt, not preaching thereupon, and procured ſcandalous and Malignant Miniſters to preach there to corrupt his people.</p>
            <p n="13">13. The Benefice of <hi>Iohn Gorſuch,</hi> Doctor of Divinity, Rector of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Walkerne</hi> in the County of <hi>Hertford,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common haunter of Ale-houſes and Tavernes, and often drunke; and oft ſitteth gaming whole nights together, and is ſeldome in the Pulpit, preaching ſcarce once a quarter; And hath often denied many of his Pariſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, without any cauſe ſhown, and refuſed to adminiſter it to ſuch as would not come up to the railes; And endeavoured to hire one <hi>Ioanes</hi> to ride a Troope-Horſe for Prince <hi>Rupert,</hi> to ſerve under him againſt the Parliament, ſaying withall, <hi>he had a ſnotty noſe Iade to ſend to the Parliament to poiſon the whole Band,</hi> and hath publiſhed a wicked Libell againſt the Parliament, <hi>That ſome of the Lords whom he Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, were Fooles, Baſtards and Cuckhoulds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. The Benefice of <hi>Edward Thurman,</hi> Rector of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Hallingbury</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a Common drunkard, and hath preſented his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners for going from their own Church to heare Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, when they had none at home; and hath affirmed, <hi>that he would drive away all the Puritans out of his Pariſh,</hi> and enforced
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112727:8"/>his Pariſhioners to come to the railes, and hath wholy deſerted his ſaid Cure for the ſpace of halfe a yeare now laſt paſt.</p>
            <p n="15">15. The Benefice of <hi>Robert Snell,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Maching</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſsex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he hath often refuſed to adminiſter the Sacrament of the Lords Supper to ſuch of his Pariſh that refuſed to come to the railes to receive it, and there being a Crucifix in the window over the Altar, he uſeth to bow towards it, and would not ſuffer it to be pulled downe, notwithſtanding the Order of Parliament for it: And hath taught his people, <hi>that God hath now an Altar, and that the Table ſet Altar-wiſe, put him in mind of God, to worſhip him the better,</hi> and in adminiſtring the Sacrament, called one of the Communicants <hi>Puppy,</hi> for that being left-handed, he put forth that hand to receive the Bread, and cauſed the Church-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens to preſent ſuch as would not come up to the railes, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive there, and kneele before them, and hath expreſſed great Malignancy againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="16">16. The Benefice of <hi>Robert Hiliard,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Ewell</hi> in the County of <hi>Surry,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he ſaid, <hi>The Parliament is a Parliament for the Devill, and the Devils Court, and that the Petitions of the Parliament to the King, are like the Petitions of</hi> Jeroboam <hi>to</hi> Rehoboam, <hi>commands and not Petitions,</hi> and hath diſcouraged divers from giving or lending towards the publike defence, expreſſing, <hi>that he hoped they that did ſo ſhould never ſee penny of it againe, and that he would rather live under the government of a Heathen, then of the Parliament,</hi> and is a common frequenter of Tavernes and Ale-houſes, ſitting tipling and quarrelling there, and is often drunke, and is a common curſer and ſwearer, and hath jeared the holy Spirit of Grace, ſaying, <hi>We have Miniſters now, will preach forſooth, and pray by the Spirit,</hi> and hath threatned to kill thoſe that have exhibited Articles againſt him in Parliament, in caſe they ſhould proceed againſt him, and went about with the Cavalieres at <hi>Kingſtone,</hi> dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting them to plunder honeſt men there.</p>
            <p n="17">17. The Benefice of <hi>Ioſeph Soane,</hi> Vicar of <hi>Aldenham</hi> in the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112727:8"/>County of <hi>Hertford,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common Gameſter, a common Ale-houſe haunter, and frequently drunke, and a common quarreller, and hath called the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Souldiers, under the command of his Excellency the Earle of <hi>Eſsex, Parliament doggs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18. The Benefices of <hi>William Fairefax,</hi> Doctor in Divinity, Rector of the Pariſh Church of S. <hi>Peters</hi> in <hi>Cornhill London,</hi> and Vicar of <hi>Eaſt-Ham</hi> in the County of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> are ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, for that he hath refuſed to deliver the Sacrament of the Lords Supper to ſuch of his Pariſhioners as refuſed to come up to the railes, and refuſed to let his Pariſh have a Lecturer on the Lords day in the after-noone, except he might have 50<hi rend="sup">lb</hi>. given unto him for the ſame: And for the ſpace of eight yeares, refuſed to let his Pariſhioners have a Lecturer on a weeke day, which was appointed, and maintenance for the ſame given by the will of the dead, and uſeth to prophane the Sabbath-day, by playing at Cards, and hath been often drunke in Ale-houſes and other places, and uſually ſeeketh and haunteth the company of women, notoriouſly ſuſpected of incontinency, and intrudes himſelfe into their company, and into the company of other women, walking alone in the ſtreetes in the darke and twi-light, and tempteth them to uncleanneſſe, leading them into darke pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and into Tavernes, fit for ſuch workes of darkneſſe, and hath expreſſed great malignity againſt the Parliament, and charged the Parliament <hi>to be the cauſe of all the trouble, and diſturbances in the Kingdome,</hi> and hath greatly neglected his Cure, and in his abſence hath provided ſcandalous Miniſters to ſupply the ſame.</p>
            <p n="19">19. The Benefice of <hi>Iames Bradſhaw,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Chalfont,</hi> S. <hi>Peters</hi> in the County of <hi>Bucks,</hi> is ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, for that he is not only a practiſer and maintainer of all the late innovations, but hath alſo preached in his Sermons, <hi>That the Commiſsaries Courts were the ſuburbs of Heaven, and the Commiſſaries and Officers of that Court, the very ſupremacies, next to Arch-Angels, and that it was a damnable ſinne for any warned to that Court not to appeare, and that to preach twice on the Lords
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112727:9"/>day is a damnable ſinne, and that to uſe any prayers beſides the Booke of Common-prayer, was likewiſe a damable ſinne,</hi> and wiſhed, <hi>that all Lecturers were hanged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20. The Benefices of <hi>Robert Cotesford,</hi> Doctor in Divinity, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Hadleigh</hi> and <hi>Munkes Ely</hi> in the County of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> are ſequeſtred, for that he is a ſtrict obſerver of the late Innovations, ſtill continues bowing towards the Eaſt in divine Service, and hath often preached for <hi>auricular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion of ſinnes, and that the reaſon why ſo many fall into deſpaire, is, becauſe they come not to their ghostly Father to confeſſe their ſinnes, and that men have by nature free-will to all good, and that Baptiſme doth waſh away originall ſinne,</hi> ex opere operato, and hath been often drunke, conſuming his time in tipling and drinking, ſometimes from morning to night, and hath oft at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted the chaſtity of his maid-ſervant, that ſhe could not live in the houſe for him, and ſeldome preacheth; and for five Moneths laſt paſt, wholy deſerted his ſaid Cures, ſo that the Church-wardens were inforced through his default, to make ſome proviſion for the ſaid Cure of <hi>Hadleigh,</hi> and hath not only refuſed to reade the Declarations of Parliament, and eſpecially that of the 22<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of <hi>October,</hi> 1643. concerning his Majeſties Commiſſions granted to Papiſts to raiſe forces, commanded to be read in Churches, but hath expreſſed otherwiſe great malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity againſt the Parliament and the proceedings thereof.</p>
            <p n="21">21. The Benefices of <hi>Nicholas Andrewes,</hi> Doctor in Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, Rector of the Pariſh Churches of <hi>Guilford,</hi> and Vicar of <hi>Godalmine</hi> in the County of <hi>Surrey,</hi> are ſequeſtred, for that he is not only negligent in preaching himſelfe, but hath alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed himſelfe to be an enemy to frequent preaching, inveigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his Sermons againſt long Sermons, ſaying, <hi>that</hi> Peters <hi>ſword cut off but one eare, but long Sermons like long ſwords, cut off both at once, and that the ſurfet of the Word is of all moſt dangerous, and that the ſillieſt creatures have longeſt eares, and that preaching was the worſt part of Gods worſhip, and that if he left out any thing, he would leave out that,</hi> and refuſed to give the Pariſhioners
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112727:9"/>leave to have a Lecturer to preach unto them, and hath preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his Pariſhioners that went to heare Sermons at other Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, when they had no preaching at home; and cauſed the Church-wardens and Sideſ-men to be preſented, for not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting ſuch into the Eccleſiaſticall court: And in delivering the Bread in the Sacrament, he elevateth it, lookes upon it, and bowes low unto it, and uſeth other frequent bowing in admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtring the Sacrament, and in his Sermons greatly exclaimes againſt that Doctrin which teacheth, <hi>that the greatest part of the world ſhould be damned,</hi> and frequenteth Tavernes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumes his time in ſitting and tipling there: And hath refuſed to publiſh the Order of Parliament, concerning the remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall of ſuperſtitious and Idolatrous pictures and Images, and hath ſubſtituted to officiate for him in the ſaid Cure, very ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous and Malignant Curates, viz. <hi>Bacock, Leverland, Paſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loe, Heath,</hi> and one <hi>Blane,</hi> who is in the Army raiſed againſt the Parliament, and when his people have propounded honeſt and Orthodox men to be his Curates, he hath refuſed them.</p>
            <p n="22">22. The Benefice of <hi>Ephraim Vdall,</hi> Rector of the Parliſh Church of S. <hi>Auſtins London,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he hath af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed, <hi>That the great reformers of the Church now were Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites;</hi> and hath made, framed and publiſhed a Booke, intituled, <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> without Licence, Charging the Parliament with Sacriledge, in endeavouring to aboliſh Epiſcopacy, and to take away the Lands of Deanes and Chapters, to amend therewith the maintenance of preaching Miniſters, and that <hi>they have thereby brought a Nationall ſinne upon the Land, as was formerly done by them in taking away the Monasteries, and that an uncleane ſpirit did breathe theſe things into their minds, a devout Devill, pretending care of Gods ſervice, and that all their goodly pretences are hipocriticall, and the maske of vile iniquity and holy theft; and that it is a thing ſenſeleſse, that Lay-men ſhould have any Tithes, and that Tithes are</hi> Jure divino, <hi>and that to alien the Lands of Cathedrall Churches, to maintaine preaching Ministers, is, to pervert the will of the dead that gave them;</hi> and otherwiſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112727:10"/>great Malignancy againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p>The Benefices of <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ieofferis,</hi> Doctor in Divinity, Vicar of the Pariſh Churches of <hi>Feverſham</hi> and <hi>Ticehurſt</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> are ſequeſtred, for that he hath preached, <hi>That the King may take not only part, but the whole of his ſubjects Estates, if it pleaſe him;</hi> And in the ſame Sermon wiſhed, <hi>that evill might befall thoſe that went about to take away governement by Biſhops, which had its plat-forme from Heaven, and that the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement by Biſhops, Priests and Deacons under the Goſpell, was from God, as under the Law, the governement of High-prieſts, Prieſts and Levites, and that he knew not from whence the Presbite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian governement came, but from</hi> Corah, Dathan <hi>and</hi> Abiram: And hath oppoſed and hindered the Lecturer from preaching a Lecture in the ſaid Church, although appointed by the Houſe of Commons thereunto; And ſaid of the Parliament, <hi>That Schiſmaticall and Pragmaticall fellowes were met together to make new Lawes;</hi> and he hath neglected the monethly Faſt, and the Lords day, there having been for divers Sabbaths, neither prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching nor prayers in the ſaid Church, and hath deſerted his ſaid Cure, for the ſpace of halfe a yeare now laſt paſt.</p>
            <p n="24">24. The Benefice of <hi>Iames Mountford,</hi> Rector of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Jewing</hi> in the County of <hi>Hertford,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that all hath refuſed to deliver the Sacrament to his Pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, for not coming up to the railes, though ſome of them begged it with teares, and openly reviled them for not confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to that ſuperſtitious Innovation, calling them <hi>Doggs, Rogues and Beggers,</hi> and preſented them to the Commiſſaries Court for the ſame, to their great damage and vexation; and hath publiſhed in his Church the Booke of Sports on the Lords day, and commended the ſame, and hath publikely in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons affirmed, <hi>That preaching is not neceſſary for the ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sabbath, and that the Sabbath was made for Ministers to reſt in as well as for the people, and that Lay-men ought not to meddle with the Scriptures, but must beleeve as the Church beleeves,</hi> which Church he made to be <hi>Arch-biſhops</hi> and <hi>Biſhops;</hi> And
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112727:10"/>the railes being removed, he placed formes inſtead of them, making his people kneele at them to receive the Lords Supper: And hath preached, <hi>That if the King ſhould ſet up flat Idolatry, we ought to ſubmit, and not to take up Armes, as ſome doe now;</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighed againſt the Parliament, for endeavouring to take away Epiſcopacy, and hath not only refuſed to joyne in the publike defence, but hath alſo diſcouraged ſuch as have ſo done.</p>
            <p n="25">25. The Benefice of <hi>Iohn Peckham,</hi> Rector of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Hosteede parva,</hi> in the County of <hi>Suſsex,</hi> who giveth out that he is the Kings Chaplaine, is ſequeſtred, for that he hath been very negligent in his Cure, abſenting himſelfe from his Pariſhioners, ſometimes a whole Moneth together, without leaving any to Officiate for him, and hath refuſed to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the Lords Supper to thoſe of his Pariſh that would not come up to the Railes; and is a common drunkard, and noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious adulterer and uncleane perſon, having drawne divers wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men to commit uncleanneſſe with him, and hath bragged, <hi>that he could lie with women, and never get them with child,</hi> and hath uſed ſordid and beaſtly carriages towards women, to intice them to ſatisfie his luſt, not to be named among the Heathen, and hath expreſſed great malignity againſt the Parliament and proceedings thereof, and hath affirmed publikely, <hi>that a man might live in murther, adultery and other groſſe ſinnes from day to day, and yet be a true penitent perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="26">26. The ſtipend of <hi>Iohn Kidd,</hi> Curate of <hi>Egerton</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he preacheth not to his Pariſh above once in a fort-night, ſometimes not once in a Moneth, or two Moneths, though there be in the ſaid Pariſh neere 400. Communicants, nor provided any other to inſtruct them, and hath uſed frequent and unreaſonable bowing to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion-Table in his ſaid Church, and perſwaded his people ſo to doe, and called them openly <hi>unreverent Puppies that paſſed by it without ſuch bowing,</hi> and in adminiſtring the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, when he had received himſelfe, and was going to adminiſter the Bread to his people, aſſaulted one of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112727:11"/>Communicants; and pulled him by the haire of the head, and thruſt him out of the Church and Congregation without any juſt cauſe, and hath never preached to his Pariſhioners upon any of the Faſt dayes.</p>
            <p n="27">27. The Benefice of <hi>Griffith Roberts,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Ridge</hi> in the County of <hi>Hertford,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he hath not only practiſed the late Innovations, and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected the publike Faſt, and imployed his neighbours to carry home wood for him upon a Faſt day, but hath openly decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Earle of <hi>Eſsex</hi> and all his followers, and Armies of the Parliament to be Traitours, <hi>and that whoſoever ſent Horſes, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney or Plate to the Parliament, were alſo Traitours, and that this Land was governed by Children and Fooles, and that the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment had done that that they muſt die for, even the beſt of them, if ever the Lawes were ſetled,</hi> and that the ſaid <hi>Roberts</hi> is a common drunkard and tipler in Ale-houſes, and drinker of healths, quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling with them that will not pledge him therein.</p>
            <p n="28">28. The Benefice of <hi>Peter Dauſem,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Camberwell</hi> in the County of <hi>Surry,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common drunkard, and drunke at the times of his officia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at Burials and Baptizings; and hath by his debauſhed converſation, diſabled himſelfe from preaching, and hath not preached for theſe 12. yeares and upwards, and did protect and hide a Romiſh Prieſt in his houſe, from the Officers that came to ſeek him, and hath extorted undue and unreaſonable fees from his Pariſhioners, and after the adminiſtring of the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, expended the money given to the poore in Sack, and dranke it in the Church; And in deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering the Sacrament to one Miſtris <hi>Wilſon,</hi> one of his Pariſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners, caſt the Bread upon the ground, ſaying to her, <hi>take it there if thou wilt have it,</hi> and is a common curſer and ſwearer, and hath read in his Church his Majeſties Declaration againſt the Parliament, concerning Levies; and being told of an Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Parliament againſt the reading of ſuch things, anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>He cared not for it.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:112727:11"/>
            <p n="29">29. The Benefice of <hi>Iohn Mountford,</hi> Doctor in Divinity, Rector of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Auſtie</hi> in the County of <hi>Hert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he hath introduced into his ſaid Church and other Churches, a turning of the Communion-Table Altar-wiſe, and having a great Crucifix and Picture of the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> in the Eaſt window over the ſaid Table, uſed bowings and cringings before the ſaid Table and Crucifix ſet Altar-wiſe, and cauſed the ſaid Table to be railed in, and the Jeſuits Badge to be ſet upon the Carpet there, compelled the people to come up to the railes, there to kneele to receive the sacrament, teaching them, <hi>that God was alwayes preſent at the Altar by the preſence of his grace, and was therefore to be bowed unto,</hi> and in his going up to the Table to reade ſecond Service, uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cauſed that part of the 43. <hi>Pſalme</hi> to be ſung, <hi>viz. Then ſhall I to the Altar goe, of God,</hi> &amp;c. And hath endeavoured to leaven his people with the doctrines of <hi>Arminianiſme,</hi> and hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, by vertue of a Commiſſary or Surrogates place he held under the Deane and Chapter of <hi>Paules,</hi> preaching in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone on the Lords day, and expounding of the Catechiſme within his Juriſdiction, only tying them to uſe the ſame by bare Queſtions and Anſwers, and preſſing the reading of the Booke of Sports on the Sabbath day, and uſually enveighed in his Sermons, againſt thoſe that went out from his ſaid Pariſh Church to heare Sermons when they had none at home, and did arreſt the Church-wardens of the ſaid Pariſh and the Gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier, for pulling downe the ſaid ſcandalous Pictures in the ſaid window, in obedience to Order of Parliament, and hath prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched againſt praying <hi>ex tempore,</hi> as unlawfull, and hath in his abſence, ſubſtituted a very ſcandalous Curate, very ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious in his practiſes, who preached <hi>that that conſcience was nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good nor quiet, that could not be content with one Sermon a day on the Lords day,</hi> and charged them as Rebells, that did not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve his ſuperſtitious practiſes of the late illegall Innovations, <hi>and that his people are bound in conſcience, to believe whatſoever he and the Doctor did preach, and that the materiall Church was the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112727:12"/>Miſticall body of Chriſt, and to give any thing to it, was to beautifie Chriſts body, and that to goe out to heare Sermons on the Lords day, when they had none at home, was ſpirituall whoredome;</hi> And the ſaid Doctor being informed of his ſaid Curates ſuperſtitious practiſes and falſe doctrines, and deſired to remove him, refuſed it; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming, <hi>that he would mainetaine him in whatſoever he had ſaid or done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="30">30. The Benefice of <hi>Edward Brewster,</hi> Rector of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Lawſhall</hi> in the County of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he hath refuſed to adminiſter the Sacrament of the Lords Supper to ſuch of his Pariſhioners as would not kneele at the railes, and after they were taken downe, from the place where they had ſtood, cauſed divers of them to be preſented in the Eccleſiaſticall Court, for not kneeling at their firſt coming into the Church, and compelled them to doe penance for the ſame, and hath refuſed to obſerve the late day of Thankeſ-giving, appointed by the Parliament, for the diſcovery of the late hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Plot againſt the City of <hi>London</hi> and the Kingdome, and is a common Ale-houſe haunter, and hath been found guilty thereof upon Inditement at the Aſſiſes, which he never traver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but ſubmitted unto a Fine thereupon, and hath continued ſince his frequent ſitting and tipling in Ale-houſes, and hath ſpoken very diſgracefully of the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed great malignancy againſt the Parliament, and neglected the keeping of the monethly Faſts, and out of meere wilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, hath refuſed to baptiſe children brought to the Church unto him for that purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="31">31. The Benefice of <hi>Richard Hart,</hi> Rector of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Hargrave</hi> in the County of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common Ale-houſe haunter, and upholder of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Ale-houſes, and commonly ſitteth drinking in them di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers dayes together, and lately continued drinking and tipling there, from Teweſday till Sunday-morning, and that morning being come home, durſt not come to Church, his face was ſo battered and beaten, and forced his Pariſhioners to goe to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112727:12"/>other Churches by reaſon of his inability to reade Divine ſervice or preach unto them; And uſed on the Lords-daies in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noones after his reading of Divine ſervice, to draw his Pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners with him to his houſe, forcing them there to drinke, untill they be drunke, cauſing every one to caſt a Dye in their courſe, and to drinke up ſo many cups as fell to their chance, perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them that if they will take their cups, he can forgive them that ſinne, and when he hath preached on the Faſt-day, hath told his Pariſhioners, that he knew not wherefore the Faſt was, and that it was not materiall to be kept, and conſumeth the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-noones of ſuch dayes in drinking with ſome of his Pariſh in his owne houſe, or at ſome private Ale-houſe. And upon Whit-ſunday laſt, though he had adminiſtred the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the fore-noone after Evening prayer read, he drew a man and his wife to a private Ale-houſe, and there kept them drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king till night, and after led them to his owne houſe, and there made the man ſo drunke, as he fell a ſleepe, and then enticed the mans wife up into his Chamber, where they were all night ſuſpitiouſly together, and drinking and taking tobacco, and hath expreſſed great malignancy againſt the Parliament, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing, <hi>he would rather carſe them, then pray for them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="32">32. The benefice of <hi>Edward Ienkinſon,</hi> Parſon of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Panfield</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſsex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he did ſet the Communion Table Altar-wiſe, and railed it in, and commanded the Church-wardens to preſent ſuch as refuſed to come and receive at the railes, and called them that refuſed, <hi>Wall-eyed Horſes,</hi> and hath in his Sermons taught, <hi>That the Table is Gods Altar, and that thoſe that would not bow here at the Name of Ieſus, ſhould bow in hell hereafter. And that ſuch as taught them they need not bow, were blind guides;</hi> And hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared the godly, reverend Miniſters, living about him to <hi>Salt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitches, which Doggs runne after, and to roasted Doggs, which draw away other mens Pigeons,</hi> becauſe his people went to heare them preach, when they had no Sermon at home. <hi>And hath ſaid, that ſuch as preach twice a day, are but praters, and that hee,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:112727:13"/>will want of his will, but he will put by preaching in the after-noone,</hi> himſelfe being a Judge in the Eccleſiaſticall Court; And he is an encourager of prophaning the Lords-day, ſending then for Cudgels for his people to play withall; and being preſent himſelf at the Cudgell playing: And hath expreſſed great malignancie againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="33">33. The Benefice of <hi>Black Novelty,</hi> alias <hi>Notly</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred from <hi>Ioſeph Plumm</hi> Parſon thereof, for that he is a common Ale-houſe and Taverne-haunter, and hath beene divers times drunke, and not onely uſed ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous bowing himſelfe at the Name Jeſus, but hath preſented the Church-wardens for not bowing, and threatned his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners, becauſe they refuſed it, commanding his Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens to looke to them, and hath abſented himſelfe from his ſaid Cure, for the ſpace of eighteene weekes laſt paſt, and is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to have betaken himſelfe to the army of the Cavaleers, and hath otherwiſe expreſſed great malignity againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p n="34">34. The Benefice of <hi>William Graunt,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Iſelworth</hi> in the County of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he hath called the ſinging Pſalmes, <hi>Hopkins Ligges,</hi> And affirmed, <hi>That he had rather heare a paire of Organs ten to one, then the ſinging of them;</hi> And hath read the Declarations and Proclamations, ſet forth by his Majeſtie againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in his Church, and hath refuſed to reade the Ordinances of Parliament, enjoyned to be read, and hath often preached againſt the preſent Defenſive Warre, averring the ſame to be againſt the Kings Perſon, and wiſhing, <hi>their hands might rot off, that ſhould be lift up therein,</hi> and preached in like manner before ſome Regiments of the Parliament ſouldiers, and hath alſo preached, <hi>That they that went about to change the Lawes and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church and Ceremonies, would at laſt change their Religion too:</hi> And hath abſented himſelfe from his ſaid Cure e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince the Kings Forces were at <hi>Branford,</hi> and hath ſaid, <hi>That the Court of Parliament, was a Court of no equitie,</hi> and affirmed,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:112727:13"/>
               <hi>the marrying of the Clergie to be the undoing of them, and that it would never be well with our Church, untill auricular Confeſſion be ſet up againe in it.</hi> And is a common haunter of Ale-houſes and Tavernes, and that on the Lords-day, even ſince the Order of Parliament for obſerving the Lords-day, and hath beene often drunke, and that many times in one weeke; And that he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, <hi>that all good fellowſhip was laid aſide in his Pariſh, but he would bring it in againe and maintaine it,</hi> and invited and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained all he could procure, to come to his houſe on Sundayes after prayers, to ſit there with him and conſume their time in drinking and tipling.</p>
            <p n="35">35. The Benefice of <hi>Henry Hancocks,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Fornax-Pelham</hi> in the County of <hi>Hertford,</hi> is ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, for that he hath preached, <hi>That it is as lawfull for a woman if ſhe diſlike her Husband, to leave him, and take another, as for one to goe out of his Pariſh to heare another Miniſter; And that to goe to another Church, was as the ſinne of Witch-craft and Idolatry,</hi> and filleth as well his Sermons as his ordinary diſcourſes, with bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter invectives and ſlanders againſt thoſe that are religiouſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, eſpecially preſenting them under the names of Puritans and Round-heads, and hath ſaid in his Sermons, <hi>That the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans forced the Parliament to make Lawes according to their own fantaſies, and not according to the Law of God;</hi> And after the fight at <hi>Edge-hill,</hi> ſaid in his Sermon, <hi>That he was overjoyed, to thinke that God ſhould put it into the heart of the King, to fight the Lords battell on the Lords day, to uphold the ould antient Catholike Faith;</hi> And fearing the pulling up of the railes about the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion-Table, he walked with his Sword about the Church-yard in the night, ſaying, <hi>he would rather looſe his life, then ſuffer them to be pul'd up, and that if the Biſhops ſhould command him to weare a Kettle upon his head, he would doe it,</hi> and is a common tipler and haunter of Ale-houſes, and a prophane ſwearer of bloudy oathes.</p>
            <p n="36">36. The Benefice of <hi>Alexander Clarke,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Bredfield</hi> in the County of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:112727:14"/>that he hath uſed very frequent bowing to the Altar, in his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and returning from it, and hath preſſed the obſerving there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of upon his Pariſhioners, and refuſed to let the Church-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens levell the ground where the Altar ſtood, becauſe it was holy and conſecrated, and not fit to be throwne out or mixed with common earth, and hath enveighed in his Sermons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginſt praying by the Spirit, calling it <hi>a Monster, conceived, borne, and dying all in an instant,</hi> and hath read the Booke of Sports on the Lords day, and incouraged his Pariſhioners to obſerve the ſame, telling them, <hi>that it was ſitter to play and follow their buſineſſe on the Lords day then on holy dayes,</hi> and hath publikely ſported himſelfe with his pariſhioners on the Lords dayes at Barly-breake, and hath taught to the people, <hi>that he hath ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute power to forgive ſinnes, blaming them that they did not ſend for their ghoſtly Father to have them forgiven,</hi> and hath ſeldome obſerved the monethly Faſt enjoyned by Parliament, and hath endeavoured to draw his Pariſhioners to the Forces raiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliament, affirming, <hi>that the Parliament had driven the King away from them, and that the proceedings of them about the King were juſt, and that there was not a Papiſt neere him;</hi> And hath affirmed, <hi>that the Earle of</hi> Strafford <hi>did die wrongfully, and that the Parliament put him to death without a cauſe,</hi> and hath ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken reproachfully of the Earle of <hi>Pembrooke,</hi> and hath threatned his neighbours to give a liſt of the Names of them to the King, that incouraged any to contribute to the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="37">37. The Benefice of <hi>Zachary Tuſham,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Dallington</hi> in the County of <hi>Suſsex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common drunkard, and hath ſolicited the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity of one <hi>Alice Thorpe,</hi> and is a common quarreller, and did way-lay one <hi>Edmund Gore</hi> about mid-night, and fell upon him, and beare him, and hath greatly neglected his Cure, ſometimes deſerting the ſame for two-Moneths together without any ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, and hath ſpoken very diſgracefully of the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and expreſſed great malignity againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="38">38. The Benefice of <hi>Nicholas Wright,</hi> Doctor in Divinity,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:112727:14"/>Rector of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Thoydon-Garnon</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he hath not preached above twice or thrice a yeare to his Pariſhioners, and yet hath preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted divers of them, and put them to great charges in the Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Courts, for going to heare Sermons in other Churches when they had none at home, and brought alſo ſuch Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters as they heard ſo preach into trouble; And hath procured the Communion-Table to be ſet Altar-wiſe, with ſtepps to it, and railes about it, and conſtantly bowed towards it at his coming and going out of the Church, refuſing to adminiſter the Sacrament to divers of his Pariſhioners without any cauſe, other then his own wilfulneſſe, and read the Booke for Sports on the Lords day in his ſaid Church, and preached to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the lawfulneſſe of it, by meanes whereof the Lords day hath ever ſince been much prophaned, by Foot-ball playing and other ungodly practiſes, and hath deſerted his ſaid Cure ever ſince <hi>Palme</hi>-Sunday laſt, and betaken himſelfe to the Army of the Cavaleeres, and is in actuall War againſt the Parliament and Kingdome. And hath brought and continued long under him for his Curate, a drunken, lewd and ſcandalous perſon, that hath been indited and found guilty at the Seſſions for a common drunkard.</p>
            <p n="39">39. The Benefice of <hi>Iohn Woodcock,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Elham</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common frequenter of Ale-houſes, and commonly drunke, and abuſeth them that will not keepe company with him at the Ale-houſe, and is a common ſwearer, by <hi>Wounds, Bloud,</hi> and other like execrable Oathes, and a common curſer, and hath deſerted his ſaid Cure ever ſince the firſt of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, and hath expreſſed great Malignity againſt the Parliament and the proceedings thereof.</p>
            <p n="40">40. The Benefice of <hi>Iohn Manby,</hi> Doctor in Divinity, Rector of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Cottenham</hi> in the County of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that while the Table was ſet Altar-wiſe, he did conſtantly bow to it eight or nine times in a fore-noone,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:112727:15"/>and though he knew that the Pariſhioners could not heare him, yet did alwayes reade ſecond Service at the Altar, and affirmed, <hi>That it was no matter whether they heard or not, for he prayed for them at the Altar,</hi> which was, <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum,</hi> and affirmed, <hi>That God was there more peculiarly preſent, then in any other place of the Church,</hi> and hath preſſed his people in his Sermons, <hi>That they ought to bring their offerings to the Altar, and offer them there to him, for that he was there in Gods ſtead to receive them,</hi> and preached, <hi>That he had power not only to pronounce abſolution, but had undoubted power to forgive ſinnes, and that the ſame was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him by the Biſhops laying on of hands, and that the Holy-dayes ought to be kept with as much reverence as the Lords day,</hi> and that he read the late new Cannons, and exhorted the people to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and obſerve them as Scripture, affirming them to be drawn out of Scripture; And refuſed to Baptiſe children brought to the Church on the Lords day at evening Prayer, though earneſtly deſired, giving no other reaſon for it, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was not his pleaſure, and hath preached openly, <hi>That Eccleſiaſticall government doth not belong to the King; but as the King had power to make Lawes to governe the Temporall eſtate by, ſo the Prelates had power to make Lawes and governe in Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call things,</hi> and hath affirmed, <hi>that he ought not to be judged by a temporall Magiſtrate,</hi> and is a common ſwearer and curſer, <hi>Woundes and Bloud,</hi> and <hi>Pox and Plague,</hi> and ſuch like horrid oathes and curſes doe commonly proceed out of his mouth, and did bragge, <hi>that he hath out-ſworne a great ſwearer,</hi> and is a fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Gameſter, even upon the Lords dayes, and when the late Innovations were growing to an height in the Church, he did openly ſay in the ſaid Church, <hi>That the Kingdome had been go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by Puritans, but now he hoped they would be rightly gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi> and hath read in his ſaid Church, all ſuch Declarations and Proclamations as came forth in the Kings name, and refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to reade the Ordinances of Parliament, or to contribute to the Parliament, or aſſociate for the publike defence.</p>
            <p n="41">41. The Benefice of <hi>William Muffet,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:112727:15"/>Church of <hi>Edmonton</hi> in the County of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common frequenter of Tavernes and Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, and a common ſwearer, curſer and blaſphemer, and is a common fighter and quarreller, not ſparing his Majeſties Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, and is commonly drunke, and ſcarcely ſober at all, but when he wanteth money to conſume in drinke, and in his drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, goeth up and downe the ſaid Towne, breaking glaſſe windowes, which hath coſt him twenty ſhillings at a time to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire, and is a common drinker of healths, and forcer of others to doe the ſame, and hath expreſſed great malignancy againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="42">42. The Benefice of <hi>Iohn Denn,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Dartford</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common Ale-houſe and Taverne haunter, and commonly drunke, and on Sabbath dayes, uſeth to ſit till twelve of the clock at night, ſending for bottles of Wine, and clubbing, and in a Sermon, deſcribed a drunkard <hi>to be only ſuch an one as lies in the Cart-way, foaming at mouth, and not able to remove from the Cart-wheeles,</hi> and refuſeth to preach on the Lords dayes, and Faſt dayes, and is unwilling to ſuffer any to doe the ſame, and hath expreſſed great malignity againſt the Parliament, and the proceedings thereof.</p>
            <p n="43">43. The Benefice of <hi>Richard Tanton,</hi> Parſon of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Ardingly</hi> in the County of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that hee is a common drunkard and Ale-houſe haunter, and in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons hath wiſhed, <hi>That every knee might rot that would not bow at the name Ieſus,</hi> and hath read in the ſaid Church, Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in his Majeſties name for raiſing of horſe and money to maintaine warre againſt the Parliament, and againſt the <hi>Militia,</hi> and hath ſtirred up his Pariſhioners to joyne with the Kings for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and hath affirmed, <hi>That he would beare out his Curate in refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to deliver the Sacrament to ſuch of his Pariſh, as would not come to the Railes to receive the Sacrament of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="44">44. The Benefice of <hi>Thomas King,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:112727:16"/>
               <hi>Cheſill magna</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common frequenter of Ale-houſes and Tavernes, and very frequently drunke, even upon Faſting-dayes, and upon the Lords-day, and hath refuſed to deliver the Sacrament of the Lords-Supper for divers yeares to his Pariſhioners that would not come up to the Railes, having ſet up the Table Altar-wiſe, and uſed bowing and cringing to it, although they did upon their knees intreate it at his hands in the Chancell, where they were wont before to receive it, and hath deſerted his Cure for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove three months, and did reade the book of ſportes in his ſaid Church for prophaning of the Sabbath.</p>
            <p n="45">45. The Benefice of <hi>Edward Alſton,</hi> Parſon of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Pentloe</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſsex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he hath attempted the chaſtity of ſome women, and hath uſed very unchaſt demeanours towards other women, ſnatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a handkerchiefe from one, and thruſting it into his bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and forcing her hand after it, and putting his yard into her hand, pulling up the coates of another, and thruſting his hand into the placket of another, and uſing other wicked temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, to draw them to his luſt, and was a forward maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and practicer of the late illegall Innovations, and hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed great Malignancy againſt the Parliament affirming, <hi>That they ſate to make Lawes by authoritie, and brake them without authority, which was meere hypocriſy.</hi> And in his Pulpit ſpake againſt the preſent defenſive warre, proteſting that now when <hi>every child lift up his Sword to ſhed innocent bloud, it was high time for him to lift up his voyce like a trumpet;</hi> And did reade in his Church Declarations ſet out in his Majeſties name, but refuſed to reade any Declarations of Parliament. And at Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas was 12. moneth having appointed a Communion, and all things were ready for it, and the Pariſhioners prepared, he tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his backe and went away, refuſing to deliver it, becauſe the Surplice was not there. And falſly affirmed, <hi>That the Parliament gathered great ſummes of money to enrich their owne purſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:112727:16"/>
            <p n="46">46. The Benefice of <hi>Chriſtopher Webb,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Sabridgworth</hi> in the County of <hi>Hertford;</hi> is ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, for that he is a Common drunkard and Ale-houſe haun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, negligent of his Cure, and not ſuffering others to preach, when himſelfe would not, and hath expreſſed much malignity againſt the Parliament, affirming among other things, <hi>That he hoped in God he ſhould ſee the Confuſion of the Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="47">47. The Benefice of <hi>Iohn Reynolds,</hi> Parſon of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Haughton</hi> and <hi>Witton</hi> in the County of <hi>Huntington,</hi> ſequeſtred for that he is a common Ale-houſe haunter and tip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler therein, and ſwearer, and in ſtead of preaching did reade the Booke of Canons, condemned in Parliament, to his people; and preſſed them to obſerve the ſame, commending them for the admirableſt things and wittieſt peece that ever was ſet forth, and affirmed, <hi>The Synod or Convocation of the Biſhops to be of more force and authoritie then all Parliaments, and to be before any of them.</hi> And hath altogether left his ſaid Cure for foure months laſt paſt.</p>
            <p n="48">48. The Benefice of <hi>Edward Aſhburnham,</hi> Vicar of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Church of <hi>Tunbridge</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common Ale-houſe haunter and Taverne haun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and very often drunke, even upon the Lords-days; and hath driven divers of his Pariſhioners with their families from their dwellings, by purſuing them for not comming up to the Railes to receive the Sacrament, and ſeldome preacheth upon the publike Faſt-days, and made a publick ſpeech for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging of the late Inſurrection and Rebellion at <hi>Tunbridge,</hi> and to contribute to the maintenance therof.</p>
            <p n="49">49. The Benefice of <hi>Nicholas Bloxam,</hi> Parſon of the Pariſh Church of great <hi>Waldingfield</hi> in the County of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> is ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, for that he is a common drunkard and inticer of others to that beaſtly vice, a common ſwearer by great and bloudy oaths; and hath bin very careleſſe and negligent of his Cure, ſeldome preaching above once a month, and never on the Faſt-dayes, and is ſeldome preſent at Church on the Paſt-dayes, and often abſent on the Lords-day, when he hath drunke hard the day before,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:112727:17"/>and hath carried himſelf very laſciviouſly towards ſeverall wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and is greatly ſuſpected of Incontinency.</p>
            <p n="50">50. The ſtipend and Benefice of <hi>Iohn Man,</hi> Curate of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Church of <hi>Stroode</hi> neare <hi>Rochester</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common drunkard and frequenter of Ale-houſes and Tavernes, drawing others to the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe with him, and is a common ſwearer by bloudy oathes, and uſeth to curſe, and is a common quarreller and fighter, and ſaid, <hi>That he ſcorned the Parliament, and that the Parliament-men were not Gentlemen of quality,</hi> and hath otherwiſe expreſſed great malignity againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="51">51. The Benefice of <hi>Nicholas Lowes,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Much-Bently</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he hath beene often drunke, and uſeth to ſit tipling in Ale-houſes ſeven or eight houres together, even on the Lords dayes, and affirmed, <hi>That he hoped to ſee them all hanged that had ſet their hands against Biſhops and Papiſts,</hi> and he and by his exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple the people ſpend the greateſt part of the Lords day in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimes and drinking at the Ale-houſe, and hath expreſſed great malignancy againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="52">52. The Benefice of <hi>William Evans,</hi> Parſon of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Sandcroft</hi> in the County of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common Ale-houſe haunter, and notorious drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard and campanion of Ale-houſe haunters, and hath altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neglected the publike Faſt, even ſince the Order of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament for the better obſervation thereof, and ſpent the ſame dayes, or the greater part of them in Ale-houſes, and wholy neglected to preach in the after-noones on the Lords day, or to ſuffer any other to doe it; And hath driven divers of his Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioners out of the Pariſh, by proſecuting them in the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Courts, for going to other Churches to heare Sermons, when himſelfe preached not, and in his Pulpit delivered, <hi>That thoſe that did give or lend to the Parliament, were accurſed,</hi> and inſteed of a Sermon on the Lords day, read to his people a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration ſet forth in his Majeſties name, concerning the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia,</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:112727:17"/>the Ships, Fortes and Towne of <hi>Hull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="53">53. The Benefice of <hi>Iohn Squire,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Shorditch</hi> in the County of <hi>Middleſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he hath publikely in his Sermons affirmed, <hi>the Papiſts to be the Kings beſt Subjects, for their Loyalty, and for their liberality, and that like</hi> Arauna, <hi>many had given like Kings to the King, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his Honour againſt the rebellious</hi> Scots, <hi>and for their patience, that enduring the many grievances under his Majeſty, they had buried all in oblivion, and the Proteſtants would afford him nothing but in a Legall way, yea but in their own way, and exhorting that none ſhould come to the Sacrament, unleſse they were ſo affected to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty as the Papists were, and compared his Majeſty, to the man that went from</hi> Hieruſalem <hi>to</hi> Jericho, <hi>and fell among theeves, that wounded him of his Honour, robbed him of his Caſtles and hearts of his people, the Prieſt paſsing by, was the Protestant, the forward pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour the Levite, but the Papiſt was the good</hi> Samaritan, <hi>eſpecially the</hi> Iriſh <hi>Papiſt, and that the Subjects and all they have, are at the Kings command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="54">54. The Benefice of <hi>Iohn Clarke,</hi> Rector of the Pariſh Church of S. <hi>Ethelburrough</hi> within <hi>Biſhops-gate London,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he hath endeavoured to corrupt his auditory with the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of Popiſh doctrine, <hi>that the Bread and Wine after the words of conſecration, ceaſe to be Bread and Wine, and differ</hi> ſpecie <hi>from what they were before, and that the Virgin</hi> Mary <hi>was the window of Heaven, and the very clouts and raggs wherein Chriſt was wrapped, were glorious raggs, and that the croſſe whereon Chriſt was crucified, was made of foure ſorts of wood,</hi> and that he is a common haunter of Tavernes and Ale-houſes, and uſeth to ſit tipling there till he be drunke, and hath expreſt great malignity againſt the power and proceedings of Parliament, ſaying, <hi>That the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment could not meddle or ſettle the buſineſſe of the Church, they being not Schollers, but Mechanick men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="55">55. The Benefice of <hi>Richard Nicholſon,</hi> Parſon of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Stapleford Tawny</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, for that he is a common drunkard and ſwearer, and hath
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:112727:18"/>expreſſed great Malignancy againſt the Parliament, ſaying, <hi>They were a company of Factious fellowes, and that this Parliament is no Parliament, and that the major part of the Lords and Commons being with the King, they were the Parliament,</hi> and uſed divers other wicked ſpeeches againſt the Parliament, and againſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Lords in the Houſe of Peeres, and had three wicked and ſcandalous Libells againſt the Parliament found in his Study, and did ſing one of them in an Ale-houſe.</p>
            <p n="36">36. The Benefice of <hi>Francis Wright,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Witham</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he hath tempted divers women, both his ſervants and Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioners to uncleanneſſe, and is a common haunter of Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes and Tavernes, and a common drunkard and prophaner of the Worſhip of God, by publike performing of the ſame in his drunkenneſſe, and a common ſwearer, and common uſer of corrupt communication, and hath not officiated in the ſaid Cure for the ſpace of twelve Moneths laſt paſt before the ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration.</p>
            <p n="57">57. The Benefice of <hi>Curthbert Dale,</hi> Rector of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Kettleburrough</hi> in the County of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> is ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, for that he was a conſtant obſerver of the late illegall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations in the Worſhip of God, and preſented and troubled his Pariſhioners in the Eccleſiaſticall Courts, for not comming up to the railes to receive the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, and not obſerving other of the ſaid Innovations, and is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſwearer and curſer, and in his Sermons hath maintained, <hi>That the Angells did mediate for the children of God, and that men might drinke one pot for neceſsity, a ſecond for recreation, and a third for good-fellowſhip, and that it is not the blood of Chriſt that takes away ſinne before God, but it is repentance and teares that waſhes away ſinnes,</hi> and hath read the Book of ſports on the Lords day, and hath ſlighted and neglected the Monethly Faſt, and ſuffered his ſervants to worke thereupon; And ſeeing a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in the Church put on his hat in Sermon time, he openly then called him, <hi>ſawcy unmannerly Clowne,</hi> and bid the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:112727:18"/>take notice of him, and the next Lords day tooke oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion in his Sermon againe to ſpeake of him being then abſent, and to call him <hi>Lobb, ſawcy Gooſe, Idiot, a Wigeon, a Cuckoe,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>he was a ſcabbed Sheepe, a ſtragler, and none of his flock,</hi> and is a common Ale-houſe and Taverne haunter, and hath been often drunke, and frequently in his Pulpit, upbraideth his Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioners, calling them <hi>Knaves, Devills, Raskalls, Rogues and Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines,</hi> uſing other opprobrious ſpeeches againſt them, and in one of his Sermons affirmed, <hi>That he hoped the late Lord</hi> Cooke <hi>was in Hell, for maintaining Prohibitions,</hi> and hath been very negligent in his Cure, oft abſenting himſelfe from it for many weekes together, and leaving the ſame in his abſence to very ſcandalous Curates, and hath wholy deſerted his ſaid Cure, for above nine weekes laſt paſt, and hath expreſſed great Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="58">58. The Benefice of <hi>Thomas Goade,</hi> 
               <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> of the Pariſh Church of <hi>East-Hatley</hi> in the County of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> is ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, for that he was for his ſcandalous life and miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, deprived of his Benefice at <hi>Guningſon</hi> in the County of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> about 20. yeares ſince, and hath not ſince re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed his life, but is ſtill a common frequenter of Ale-houſes, and very often drunke, and oft on the Lords day; And on <hi>Newyeares</hi>-day was twelve-moneth, the Sacrament of the Lords Supper being to be adminiſtred in his Church, he came from an Ale-houſe where he had been all night, and was ſo drunke, that he fell downe twice or thrice in the preſence of the Pariſhioners, who expected him at the Church-doore; And hath beene oft likewiſe drunke when he ſhould have been preaching, and taken up drunke in the Church-yard coming to performe that duty, by reaſon whereof, divers times his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners have had neither prayers nor preaching on the Lords day; And hath oft ſate ſo long drinking, that he hath bepiſt himſelfe, and ſometimes the roome where he ſate, and is an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragious common ſwearer and curſer, and in his Tipling uſeth to ſay, <hi>Now Devill, doe thy worſt,</hi> and cauſed his ſervants to goe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:112727:19"/>to their earthly laboures upon the Faſt-dayes, and finding his neighbours Hoggs treſpaſſing, wiſhed <hi>the plague of God in Hell might take her and her Hoggs,</hi> and hath been a great practiſer and preſſer of the late illegall Innovations in the Worſhip of God; And becauſe his Pariſhioners would not come up to the railes to receive, cauſed the Pariſh-Clarke to carry away the Bread and Wine, and hath expreſſed great malignancy againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="59">59. The Benefice of <hi>Nicholas King,</hi> Vicar of <hi>Friſton</hi> and <hi>Snape</hi> in the County of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common Ale-houſe haunter, and companion of ſcandalous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and men of evill fame, and oft drunke, and attempted the chaſtity of <hi>Elizabeth Scotchmer,</hi> who going to his houſe to pay him ſome moneyes, he inticed her to lye with him, and did ſtrive a long time with her to abuſe her by force, and would have corrupted her thereunto with moneyes, but ſhe proteſting unto him ſhe would not ſell her ſoule to the Devill for money, he replied to her, <hi>She was a foole, for God did forgive the greateſt ſinners,</hi> and hath expreſſed great malignancy againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</p>
            <p n="60">60. The Benefice of <hi>Edward Turner,</hi> Parſon of the Pariſh Church of S. <hi>Lawrence</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common ſwearer, and common Ale-houſe haun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſtrong to beare ſtrong drinke, and uſeth to ſit five or ſix houres together tipling at Tavernes, ſometimes whole dayes and nights tipling and drinking, and ſometimes drunke, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon practiſer and preſſer of the late illegall Innovations, and hath deſerted his Cure for the ſpace of a yeare now laſt paſt.</p>
            <p n="61">61. The Benefice of <hi>Iohn Wells,</hi> Parſon of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Shimplyn</hi> in the County of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common Ale-houſe haunter and common drunkard, and in his drunkenneſſe hath layne abroad in the fields, loſt his hat, fallen into ditches, and ſo bemired himſelfe, that he hath been faine to be waſhed, and hath attempted the chaſtity of divers women, and ſould his Calves for kiſſes with them, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:112727:19"/>having lockt himſelfe up in a chamber in an Inne with a lewd woman, after a long time the doore was broken open upon him, upon his refuſall to unlock it, and he found in a very ſuſpitious manner upon a bed with her, after which he conveyed her ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly away, and ſent guifts unto her; And hath affirmed, <hi>That the Land was governed by wicked men, and that the Papists were the Kings best ſubjects,</hi> and is a common ſwearer of very great Oathes.</p>
            <p n="62">62. The Benefice of <hi>Thomas Geary,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Beddingfield</hi> in the County of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common frequenter of Ale-houſes, often drunke even to vomit, and hath been and is a common ſwearer of bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy oathes, and curſer in a fearfull manner, as <hi>God damne me, the Devill damne me,</hi> refuſed to preach for many Sabbath dayes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and ſaid, <hi>he thought preaching would doe his Pariſhioners no good,</hi> and uſeth in his Sermons to raile upon his Pariſhioners, calling them, <hi>ſowded Piggs, Bursten Rammes, and ſpeckled Frogs,</hi> and one of the chiefe women of the Pariſh, greatly grieved at ſuch miſcarriages, and going out of the Church, the ſaid <hi>Geary</hi> openly in his Pulpit thereupon ſaid, <hi>that if there were but one Whore in the Pariſh, ſhe would kick and fling, and never keepe her ſeate,</hi> and affirmed, <hi>that he had abſolute power to forgive ſinnes,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>that though this doctrine had laine hid for many yeares, yet he bleſſed God that it was now revived againe,</hi> and on a Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day diſheartend men from attending on that ſacred Ordinance, and was a great promotor, practiſer and urger of the late illegall Innovations, and when the railes were taken away, affirmed, <hi>that the place was the worſe for thowant of them,</hi> and hath expreſſed great malignancy againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="63">63. The Benefice of <hi>Thomas Darnell,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Thorpe</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is an uſuall prophaner of the Lords day, by ſports and playes, and by making cleane his Cow-houſe and out-houſes, and other like ſervile workes, and read the Book of ſports on the Lords day in the Church, with approbation thereof, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:112727:20"/>is a common ſwearer and curſer, and a notorious drunkard and Ale-houſe haunter, even upon the Faſt-dayes, and is a common Gameſter at unlawfull games, and hath been convicted of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continency and adultery before Doctor <hi>Warren</hi> and others, Juſtices of peace, and began ſuite at Law in an action of ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for the ſame, but durſt never proceed therein, and hath prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, <hi>That he that would not conforme to his Prince in any Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, ought to be burnt,</hi> and was a conſtant practiſer of the late Innovations, and put ſuch of his Pariſh from the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, as would not come to receive it at the railes, and hath expreſſed great malignancy againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="64">64. The Benefice of <hi>Iohn Wood,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Marden</hi> in the county of <hi>Kent,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he did reade the Booke of ſports upon the Lords day in his Pariſh Church, and did preach for the maintenance thereof, and is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly infamous for ſundry adulteries, a common Ale-houſe haunter, oft drunke, a common gameſter and quarreller in ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, a great ſwearer, and was puniſhed at a quarter Seſſions for adultery, committed with the Wife of one <hi>Prior</hi> of the ſaid Pariſh, and having contracted one <hi>Margaret Parkes</hi> his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to <hi>Thomas Mapleſden,</hi> his own Wife happening to die, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards tooke to Wife the ſaid <hi>Margaret,</hi> againſt the will of the ſaid <hi>Thomas Mapleſden;</hi> And on the Faſt-dayes, uſeth to ſit drinking and tipling two or three houres together in an Ale-houſe, in the company of other mens wives, by him ſeduced thereunto, and hath ſaid, <hi>That the Parliament hath no power to doe any thing in the Kings abſence, no more then a man without a head,</hi> and hath otherwiſe expreſſed great malignity againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="65">65. The Benefice of <hi>Thomas Heny,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Arundell</hi> in the County of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common frequenter of Ale-houſes and Tavernes, and hath beene often drunke, a common ſwearer, and hath oft procured Ale-houſes to be ſet up in by-corners of the ſaid Towne in deſpite of the Magiſtrate, and not onely preacheth
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:112727:20"/>very ſeldome himſelfe, except it be for ſpeciall reward, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeth to ſuffer others to preach to his Pariſhioners, when him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe doth not, and checks them for deſiring preaching ſo much, telling them, <hi>That he would make them content with a Homily, and before he had done with them, would make them glad with one Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in a moneth:</hi> And by his power in the Eccleſiaſticall Courts, hath cauſed ſcandalous perſons to be placed for ſchool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters in the ſaid Towne to corrupt the youth, and hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed great malignancie againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="66">66. The Benefice of <hi>Eraſmus Laud,</hi> Rector of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Little-Tey</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common drunkard, even on the Lords day, thereby diſabling himſelfe to officiate his Cure, and ſitting drinking late on a Satur-day night, was demanded, who ſhould preach on the next day, he anſwered, <hi>Let the devill preach, give me another cup of ſacke,</hi> and is a common ſwearer, and hath uſed frequent ſuperſtitious cringing to the Altar, and ſeldome preacheth to his Pariſhioners, not above once in five or ſix weekes before the Parliament, and divers times through his neglect, his Church-doores have beene ſhut up all day on the Lords-dayes and Faſt-dayes, and at thoſe times ſet his ſervants to worke, and did work himſelf with them.</p>
            <p n="67">67. The Benefice of <hi>Anthony Hugget,</hi> Parſon of the Pariſh Church of the <hi>Cliffe</hi> in the County of <hi>Suſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he hath preached, <hi>that it was more lawfull to steale or doe ſervile workes upon the Lords day, then to goe to other Churches to heare a Sermon, when there was none at home:</hi> And hath ſued di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of his Pariſhioners for going to other Churches to heare Sermons, when he preached not, and forced two of them to doe pennance for it, and to acknowledge openly, <hi>That they had offended God in it, and grieved, and gave offence to their fellow-Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners,</hi> And procured one of them to be excommunicated for it. And put one <hi>Peter Pennell,</hi> whom he had 7. yeares before ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the communion, from the Sacrament of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, becauſe he would not come among the boyes to be cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chized;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:112727:21"/>and likewiſe refuſed to deliver the Sacrament to <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Pennell,</hi> becauſe he was lame and could not kneele to receive it. And hath beene bound at the generall quarter Seſſions to his good behaviour for ſeverall Miſdemeanours, and in ſtead of a Sermon on the Lords day, did reade to his people the late new Canons, and is greatly ſuſpected of Incontinency, and hath had the French-pox, and was cured thereof by one M. <hi>Abell</hi> for 10. pound promiſed him. And the ſaid <hi>Huggets</hi> wife, asking him for a peece of gold, which he tooke from her, and gave to a light woman, in furie he ſpurned her on the belly, when ſhee was quicke with child, ſo that ſhe was forced preſently to take her chamber, and was delivered of a dead child, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding wch he vowed he would never have more children by her: And hath wholy deſerted his Cure for above 6 months from the time of the ſaid ſequeſtration, and hath been ſeene in the Army of Cavaleers raiſed againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="68">68. The Benefice of <hi>Iohn Sydall,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Kenſworth</hi> in the county of <hi>Hertford,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that hee is a common frequenter of Ale-houſes, and commonly drunke, and hath ſeverall times refuſed to adminiſter the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament to ſuch as would not come up to the Railes to receive the ſame. And when the Railes were taken away, ſaid it was <hi>the beginning of the abomination of Deſolation, and that Whore-mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and Drunkards are as excuſable as thoſe that goe from their owne Pariſh to heare Srrmons, and that Papists were better Subjects then Puritans:</hi> And hath neglected his Cure for ſeverall Lords dayes without any ſupply, and hath expreſſed great malignancy againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="69">69. The Benefice of <hi>Iohn Rannew,</hi> Parſon of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Kettlebaſton</hi> in the county of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common Ale-houſe haunter, and much given to tipling and drinking, and uſeth to provoke others to the ſame, and hath been often-times drunke, and hath preached in his Sermons, <hi>That Originall ſinne is waſhed away in baptiſme:</hi> And read the booke of ſports on the Lords day, and encouraged his
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:112727:21"/>Pariſhioners to practiſe the ſame, and hath procured ſome of his pariſhioners to be puniſhed in the Commiſſaries court, for go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to heare Sermons in other Churches when they had none at home; and hath ſundry times wholy neglected the monethly Faſt, and employed his ſervants in their weekely labours and worke on the ſame; And hath been a zealous practiſer of the late illegall Innovations, and hath wholy deſerted his Cure for halfe a yeare and upwards.</p>
            <p n="70">70. The Benefice of <hi>Ieoffrey Anherſt,</hi> Doctor in Divinity, Rector of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Horſemauden</hi> in the county of <hi>Kent,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he hath been a diligent practiſer of the late illegall Innovations in the Worſhip of God, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to adminiſter the Sacrament to thoſe that would not come up to the railes, reproaching ſuch as would not comply with him in thoſe Innovations, as ſuch as ſhall have no part with the Saints in light, nor inherit the Kingdome of Heaven, and is a common ſwearer and haunter of Ale-houſes, and hath been often and extreamely drunke, and hath wholy deſerted his ſaid Cure for above ſeven Moneths laſt before the ſaid ſequeſtration, and hath expreſſed great malignity againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="71">71. The Benefice of <hi>Miles Goultie,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Walton</hi> in the county of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a great practiſer and preſſer of the late illegall Innovations in the Worſhip of God, and hath refuſed to give the Sacrament to his pariſhioners that would not come up to the railes to receive the ſame, and being preſſed much by his pariſhioners to preach twice a day, or to give them leave to procure one to doe it, he utterly refuſed, profeſſing he would bring no ſuch new orders among them, and in his Sermons uſually enveighs againſt his pariſhioners for going to heare Sermons at other Churches when they had none at home, and finding his Curate painefull in preaching twice on the Lords day, he put him away, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained in his roome a moſt drunken ſcandalous and idle Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and is a common frequenter of Tavernes and Ale-houſes,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:112727:22"/>ſitting ripling there foure or five dayes in a weeke, and oft till mid-night, and hath been often drunke, and hath expreſſed great malignancy againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="72">72. The Benefice of <hi>Samuel Alſop,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Acton</hi> in the county of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he hath attempted the chaſtity of divers married women, and frequented the company of women greatly ſuſpected to be lewd and of ill fame, and got a maid with child in the houſe where he ſojourned, and hath ſet up in his chancell the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits Badge in gold, in divers places thereof, and hath expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed great malignancy againſt the Parliament, and hath wholy deſerted his ſaid Cure for halfe a yeare laſt paſt before the ſaid ſequeſtration.</p>
            <p n="73">73. The Benefice of <hi>Robert Senior,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Feering</hi> in the county of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common frequenter of Ale-houſes, and commonly drunke, and hath been admoniſhed by his Ordinary for it, and yet hath not left it, and was for his continuance therein ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Ordinary, and yet ſtill perſiſteth in the ſame, and commonly marries any manner of perſons even without li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, and of the monethly Faſt ſaid, <hi>he wondred who a pox devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it,</hi> and ſware <hi>by his Maker, that he would preach no more on it,</hi> and hath expreſſed great malignancy againſt the Parliament, and great affection to the Cavaleeres, and Army raiſed againſt the Parliament, as more ſuitable to his ſpirit.</p>
            <p n="74">74. The Benefice of <hi>Henry Kybert,</hi> Parſon of the Pariſh Church of S. <hi>Katherine-Coleman London,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he got into the ſaid pariſh indirectly, by meanes of a falſe <hi>Certificate,</hi> ſubtilly procured by falſe ſuggeſtions, from divers of the pariſhioners of the ſaid pariſh, who having complained and Articled againſt him and <hi>Percivall Hill</hi> his predeceſſor, for great miſdemeanours, pretended <hi>that he was upon ſome hope of preferment elſe where, and that if his pariſhioners would ſubſeribe to a Certificate and teſtimoniall of his good behaviour, they ſhould be rid of him,</hi> and having thereby obtained ſuch ſubſcriptions,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:112727:22"/>the ſaid <hi>Hill</hi> and he went to the Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> Patron of the ſaid Church, and the ſaid <hi>Hill</hi> to flie from the cenſure of Parliament upon the ſaid Articles, reſigned the ſaid Church, and upon vehement affirmation, <hi>that the ſaid Certificate was true and fairely gotten,</hi> procured the ſaid Biſhop to preſent the ſaid <hi>Kybert</hi> to the ſaid Church, who was thereupon inſtituted and inducted; And the ſaid <hi>Kybert</hi> is a common frequenter of Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernes and Ale-houſes, and commonly frequents the company of a married woman of very ill fame, and hath been ſeen to imbrace and kiſſe her very laſciviouſly, and hath been in a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuſpitious manner in private with her, and hath not been a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed in Divine-ſervice, publikely to expreſſe unſeemely ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures and behaviours towards her in the Church; and being told that he was ſeen to be in ſuch private miſcarriage with her, anſwered, <hi>that he would after be more cautions,</hi> which according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he obſerved, reſorting commonly to her houſe afterwards by night and not by day, and hath ſince his inſtitution into the ſaid Church, ſeldome preached, and in his abſence committed the Cure to drunken, lewd and laſcivious Curates, and hath been a great practiſer and preſſer of the late illegall Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in the Worſhip of God, and hath expreſſed great malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy againſt the Parliament, and hath deſerted his ſaid Cure, for more then foure Moneths laſt paſt before the ſaid ſequeſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="75">75. The Benefice of <hi>Walter Mattock,</hi> Parſon of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Storrington</hi> in the county of <hi>Suſsex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a zealous practiſer of the late illegall Innovations, and hath not preached above once or twice in foure or five yeares in his Pariſh, and refuſeth to Church women if they have not on a Vaile, and come not up to the raile, and hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven his Curate charge to obſerve the ſame; And is a common ſwearer and curſer, and a common gameſter at Cards and Dice, and uſeth to ſit tipling with looſe and lewd companions, and hath been over-ſeen in drinke, and hath ſaid, <hi>That none but a company of giddy-headed fellowes would preach twice a day,</hi> and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:112727:23"/>cauſed and countenanced the reading of the Book of Sports in his Church to prophane the Lords day, and hath ſent his Armes to aſſiſt the illegall <hi>Commiſsion of Array,</hi> and to oppoſe the Forces of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and hath otherwiſe expreſſed great malignancy againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and hath wholy deſerted his ſaid Cure ever ſince the firſt of <hi>February</hi> laſt.</p>
            <p n="76">76. The Benefice of <hi>Clement Vincent,</hi> Rector of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Danbury</hi> in the county of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a great practiſer of the late illegall Innovations, and doth not only encourage ſports and playing on the Sabbath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day before his own doore, but hath alſo been a practiſer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe thereof, giving ill example thereby, and neglected the keeping of the monethly-Faſt, and inſtead of faſting, ſuffered on the Faſt-day, Foot-ball playing in his own ground, himſelfe being a ſpectator thereof, and is a common drunkard, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſwearer and curſer, and hath expreſſed great malignancy againſt the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="77">77. The Benefice of <hi>Matthew Clay,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Chelſworth</hi> in the county of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he hath very little reſided upon his Parſonage-houſe, but letteth one live in it that turneth it to an Ale-houſe, in which there is very much diſorder, even upon the Lords dayes, and hath neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected the obſervation of the monethly-Faſt, affirming <hi>that the time for them is expired,</hi> and is a common ſwearer, a haunter of Ale-houſes and Tavernes, and hath been oft very drunke; And hath often preached, <hi>That ſinnes of ignorance and ſinnes of infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity doe not grieve the Spirit of God,</hi> and hath expreſſed great malignancy againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and hath wholy deſerted his ſaid Cure for above foure Moneths before the ſaid ſeque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, leaving upon his departure a ſcandalous Curate, a drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard that ſtate in the ſtocks for his miſdemeanours, and for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Lords-dayes the Church doores have been ſhut up, and the Pariſh left without prayer or preaching.</p>
            <p n="78">78. The Benefice of <hi>Daniel Horſmande<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> Doctor in Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, Parſon of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Vlcomb</hi> in the county of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:112727:23"/>
               <hi>Kent,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he did affirme, <hi>That the late Deputy of</hi> Ireland <hi>was put to death wrongfully, and was ſacrificed as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Chriſt was, to give the people content,</hi> and is and hath been for eleven yeares laſt paſt, a common haunter of Ale-houſes and Tavernes, and very often exceeding drunke, and hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed great malignity againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and preached, <hi>That to heare a Sermon on the weeke dayes, was a will-worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="79">79. The place and ſtipend of <hi>Ioſeph Daves,</hi> Curate and Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitler of S. <hi>Thomas</hi> Hoſpitall in <hi>Southwarke,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common drunkard, and common haunter of Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernes and Alehouſes, and a common ſwearer, and hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed great malignancy againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> affirming them, to be all <hi>Rogues, and that he was conſident God would ſhew no mercy to them that died in the Parliaments ſervice, and that all that went forth in their ſervice, were Rogues and Raſcals, and that thoſe that died in their ſervice at</hi> Edge-<hi>Hill went to the Devill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="80">80. The Benefice of <hi>Henry Oſbalſton,</hi> Doctor in Divinity, Parſon of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Much-Parudon</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he in his abſence, ſupplied his ſaid Cure by ſcandalous and inſufficient Curates, and hath in his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons preached againſt <hi>frequent preaching,</hi> affirming it <hi>to be proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no ſervice of God, and that it was never a merry world ſince there was ſo much of it; and that if he could preach twice a day, he would not, and that once hearing of Common-prayer, is better then</hi> 10. <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> and hath read in his ſaid Church, the Booke of Sports on the Lords-day, and encouraged men to Foot-ball and other like ſports on that day; and hath taught his people, <hi>That the water in Baptiſme doth waſh away originall ſinne,</hi> and being deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to pray for a ſick child that was two yeares old, ſaid in his prayer, <hi>That actuall ſinne it had committed none, and as for ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall, it was done away at Baptiſme,</hi> and hath preſſed his pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioners to come up to the railes to receive the Sacrament, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing <hi>that otherwiſe he would not deliver it unto them;</hi> And hath threatned to preſent ſuch of his pariſhioners as went to heare Sermons elſewhere, when they had none at home, calling them
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:112727:24"/>
               <hi>Hypocrites, and of the tribe of God,</hi> and ſaid to one of his pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioners, <hi>that he could not abide him, becauſe he ſhanke of two Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons a day;</hi> And being demanded to contribute to the aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Counties for the publike defence, ſaid <hi>he would firſt have his throate cut before he would.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="81">81. The Benefice of <hi>Humphrey Dawes,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Mount-Nezing</hi> in the county of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he hath diſcouraged his pariſhioners from aſſiſting the preſent defenſive War, affirming, <hi>That they are damned and are Traitors to the King, that have lent money to the Parliament,</hi> and that he hath read the Book of Sports; and incouraged his pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioners to prophane the Sabbath, and hath been often drunke, and came ſo drunke to Church on the Lords day, as he bad his people ſing a Chapter in the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> for a <hi>Pſalme,</hi> not knowing what he did.</p>
            <p n="82">82. The Benefices of <hi>Richard Taylor,</hi> Parſon of the Pariſh Churches of <hi>Buntingford, Westmill</hi> and <hi>Aſpeden</hi> in the county of <hi>Hertford,</hi> are ſequeſtred, for that he hath not only uſed fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent bowing to the Communion-Table ſet Altar-wiſe, but affirmed, <hi>That there was a more peculiar preſence of God there then in the Church,</hi> and hath compelled his people to come up to the railes to receive the Sacrament, refuſing to adminiſter to ſuch as ſcrupled to doe it; and there being a Croſſe at the head of the Font in his Church, upon every approach towards the Font, uſed to bow to it, and urged ſome of the pariſh to make <hi>auricular confeſsion</hi> to him, affirming <hi>that he could forgive them,</hi> and having the Office of Surrogate in the Eccleſiaſticall Court, he did improve his authority to introduce the late In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations into the Church, and in his preaching alſo preſſed his people to bow three times at their comming into the Church, and keepeth a picture of Chriſt in his Parlour, which hee hath confeſſed, <hi>was to put him in mind of his Saviour,</hi> and hath affirmed the fourth Commandement, to be <hi>meerely cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall,</hi> and accordingly uſeth to hire ſervants, ride journeyes, buy wood, and ſend his Hopps to market on the Lords day,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:112727:24"/>and upon the diſſolution of a late Parliament, he ſaid, <hi>If he were as the King, he would never have Parliament more, while he lived:</hi> And affirmed, <hi>that the last Parliament was the weakest that ever ſate,</hi> becauſe they went about to queſtion the Kings ſervants and the Miniſters that went to the Table to ſay ſecond Service, and ſaid, <hi>There was no need of a Parliament, for the King might have money another way;</hi> and charged this Parliament with doing great wrong in committing and executing the Earle of <hi>Strafford,</hi> and would neither preach on the Sabbath daies in the after-noone, nor ſuffer others to preach, though he could doe it, as he ſaid, with halfe an houres ſtudy, and proſecuteth his people for going to other Churches to heare Sermons, when they had none at home, and hath expreſſed great malignity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliament, and refuſed to publiſh the Proteſtation, and hath deſerted his cure ever ſince a fort-night before Eaſter laſt.</p>
            <p n="83">83. The Benefice of <hi>Thomas Baily,</hi> Rector of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Braſteed</hi> in the county of <hi>Kent,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he hath endeavoured to corrupt his people with the leaven of falſe Doctrine, teaching them, that <hi>ex tempore prayer was Phariſaicall at the beſt, and that no prayer ought to be longer then the Lords prayer, and that people ought not to pray privately or ſecretly any prayer that was not first written, and ſhewed to and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by a Prieſt, That though people confeſſe their ſinnes to God, yet they ought for more ſurety of forgiveneſse to confeſſe them to their Prieſt, their ghoſty Father, and that for want of auricular Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſome have beene brought to confeſse at the Gallowes.</hi> And hath laboured by his preaching and otherwiſe to draw his people to auricular confeſſion, averring that <hi>he had power to abſolve them, and that the Priest, though wicked, had power to forgive others ſins, though not his owne, and that ſuch as refuſed to give their children and ſervants liberty on the Lords day, after their obſervation of the time of publike-worſhip, to ſport and play, did breake Gods Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. That Offering on the Altar upon their knees is of abſolute neceſſity;</hi> and accordingly, while the Church-wardens are col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:112727:25"/>the monies, given at the Sacrament, he uſeth to ſuſpend the celebration thereof, and when it is brought up to the Table takes it from them, layes it on his booke, bleſſeth it, offers it up, and re-delivers it unto them, and then proceeds. And hath alſo publikely preached, <hi>That it is a great griefe to Gods people, that Abbies are not againe erected, becauſe divers could not endure to live publikely, &amp; that the curſe of God was on them that kept the Abby-Lands, and therefore they did not proſper.</hi> That he turned the communion-Table Altar-wiſe, railed it in, uſed frequent bowing before it, urged his people to come thither to receive, ſet the Jeſuites badge with a glory about it over the communion-Table on the Eaſt-wall, and on the north-wall neare the Altar, cauſed the picture of a flying Dove to be ſet over the Font to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the Holy Ghoſt, altered the deske in the Church to a place in the chancell, where he was not ſeene nor heard of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in the Church, and hath refuſed to reade the Act of 21. <hi>Iaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi,</hi> againſt ſwearing, ſaying, he knew a better meanes to helpe it, namely by confeſſion and pennance. And hath refuſed to reade the buriall ſervice at the buriall of ſome children, becauſe they dyed before Baptiſme, and in viſiting the ſicke, uſeth to mumble ſomewhat overthem, and then to croſſe them upon the face and the fore-head, and hath expreſſed great malignity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="84">84. The Benefice of <hi>Richard Duxon</hi> Doctour in Divinitie, parſon of the Pariſh Church of St. <hi>Clement-Danes</hi> without Temple-barre London, is ſequeſtred, for that in his cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſing in his ſaid Church he hath taught, <hi>That children dying after Baptiſme are ſaved by the faith of the God-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and God-mothers:</hi> And ſpendeth much of his time in gaming for money, and uſeth to ſweare by the faith of a Prieſt before God, and upon his ſalvation, and is very ſuperſtitious in bowing and cringing to the Altar, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing the late illegall Innovations, and compared them that vſed <hi>ex tempore</hi> prayer, and enlarged themſelves therein with pertinent expreſſions, to <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts, who thought to be heard
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:112727:25"/>for their much bauling. And neglecting to preach himſelfe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Christmas</hi>-day laſt in the after-noone, and finding a very great congregation met to heare M. <hi>Evans</hi> the Lecturer preach, kept the Pulpit and deske himſelfe, with a ſtrong hand, refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to let the Lecturer preach, and openly proteſted to the congregation, that they ſhould have no Sermon then; and in the pulpit read a few collects to them, and then charged the Church-wardens to drive the congregation out, or to ſhut them in, and ſo inforced the congregation to depart without any Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in great diſcontent: And ſpeaking of the preſent troubles ſaid, <hi>It had beene a happy thing for the Kingdome, if they had made choice of ſuch Parliament-men, as they might have truſted without any Puritans.</hi> And reading in his Church an Ordinance of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament for a collection for maimed ſouldiers, to diſcourage his people from giving to that pious uſe, told them, <hi>That charitie did begin at home, and for his part, he thought their own poore had more need of it,</hi> And hath not onely refuſed to take the late Proteſtration, but alſo being deſired to lead his people in taking the late Covenant, anſwered openly in the Church before them, <hi>That he would not lead the people into ſinne,</hi> and yet was a great promoter of the Church-wardens and Sideſ-men of the ſaid Pariſh to take the Oath of the late new Canons with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and hath otherwiſe expreſt great malignity againſt the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and hath extorted exceſſive fees from his Pariſhioners for burials, <hi>viz.</hi> twenty ſhillings for a Sermon, when there was none, twelve ſhillings for the uſe of a black-cloath, han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged about the Pulpit at the time of the buriall, not being deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and otherwiſe, and hath deſerted his cure for ſix weekes laſt paſt, before the ſaid ſequeſtration, and hath betaken him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the Army of cavaleers, raiſed againſt the Parliament, and was ſeene in <hi>Oxon</hi> ſince in a coloured hat and coat.</p>
            <p n="85">85. The Benefices of <hi>Edward Marten,</hi> Doctor in Divinity, Parſon of the Pariſh Churches of <hi>Houghton-Conquest</hi> in the county of <hi>Bedford,</hi> and of <hi>Dunnington</hi> in the county of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> is ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtred, for that he uſually prayed openly <hi>for the Saints and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:112727:26"/>people departed this life, and that they may be eaſed and freed of their paines in Purgatory,</hi> and hath ſaid, <hi>that preaching is prophaned when it is in a dining-roome, or other place, not hallowed by the Biſhop, and that the Ordinance is prophaned by the place, and doth not conſecrate the place:</hi> And that having great yearely revenues, did notwithſtanding upon the Sabbath-day ſteale wheate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheaves out of the field in harveſt, and laid them to his tithe ſhock, and hath not preached ſince he was Parſon of <hi>Hough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton-Conqueſt</hi> in five yeares, not above five Sermons there, and hath ſubſtituted there in his abſence very ſcandalous and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant Curates, and was a great promoter of the late new Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, and is moſt unreaſonable in adoring of the Altar, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king five low curſies in his going to it, and two at it, and then falling downe upon his knees before it, with his eyes on a cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifix, being in the Eaſt window over it. And when hee did preach, his Subject was moſtly in exalting of holy ground, and preſſing the practiſe of the ſaid illegall Innovations, and he forced divers women that came to be churched to come up to the Altar; and there to ducke and kneele unto it, and at their comming and going from it, and had made his Pariſhioners, not onely to cringe to the ſaid Table, and come up to the Rails, but alſo to offer money there unto him, holding a baſon for the fame purpoſe on his knees, commanding them ſo to offer their gifts. And hath openly preached that the Parliament goeth about in a factious way, to erect a new Religion, and hath confeſſed before the Committee of the Houſe of Commons in Parliament concerning plundered Miniſters, that hee had lent and given money to the King to maintaine this unnaturall warre againſt the Parliament and Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="86">86. The Benefice of <hi>Iames Buck,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Stradbrocke</hi> in the county of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he hath preached openly, <hi>That the Pope is the head of the Church, and head of the ſpiritualty, and that there would never be any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity in the Church, till a Patriarch ſhould be above a Biſhop, a Biſhop above a Prieſt, a Priest above a Deacon, and the Biſhop of</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:112727:26"/>Rome <hi>above them all. And that</hi> this is my Body <hi>in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Supper is to be underſtood in the literall ſenſe, and that there is a Tranſmutation of the bread and wine into the body and bloud of Chriſt,</hi> as in John 2. <hi>the ſubſtance of water is turned into the ſubſtance of wine. And that the words,</hi> Doe this, <hi>are ſpoken to the Priest to create the body of our Lord,</hi> affirming, <hi>the Prieſt to to have power to create the very body and bloud of Chriſt, and that it is lawfull to invocate Saints and Angels, and that Infants dying after Baptiſme, become Interceders, even for their Parents: And that auricular Confeſsion to the Priest is abſolutely neceſſary to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, once a yeare, or at leaſt once in a mans life.</hi> And hath alſo laboured to maintaine <hi>univerſall grace, and that the Church of</hi> Rome <hi>is as honourable a Church as any in the world:</hi> And that he uſeth to make as low obeyſance at the mentioning of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Maries</hi> name, as he doth at the name Jeſus. And doth not onely bow thrice at his going, and thrice at his returne from the Communion Table ſet Altar-wiſe; But teacheth, <hi>That Adoration is due to it, when the holy myſteries are abſent; and that it is as lawfull to worſhip the Altar, as for the woman that touched the hem of his garment to worſhip Chriſt, and as it was for the</hi> 24. <hi>Elders in the</hi> Revelation <hi>to worſhip before the Throne,</hi> And hath refuſed to deliver the Sacrament of the Lords-Supper to divers of his Pariſhioners, though they deſired it on their knees at the Railes, meerely upon his owne will, and denied the cup to divers to whom he gave the bread, and hath often preached, <hi>That if a child die baptized, it is undoubtedly ſaved, but if it die before baptiſme, it is undoubtedly damned,</hi> and hath expreſſed great malignancy againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <p n="87">87. The Benefice of <hi>Thomas Vaughan,</hi> Curate of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Chatham</hi> in the county of <hi>Kent,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he hath beene a great practiſer of the late illegall ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious Innovations and preſſer of the ſame upon the conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his auditory, proteſting againſt them that would not comply with him therein, as men of a devilliſh ſpirit, and hath been very negligent in his Cure, many times not prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:112727:27"/>above once a moneth, and affirmed, <hi>That to preach in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is to preach on Sundaies in the fore-noone, and out of ſeaſon in the after-noon:</hi> And endeavoured to hinder his pariſhioners from going to heare Sermons elſe where, when they had none at home, affirming to them, <hi>That it was as lawfull for him to uſe Dalliance, or lie with his neighbours wiſe, as for any of them to goe from their owne Pariſh.</hi> And is a common frequenter of tavernes, ſitting a tipling there, and hath been often drunke, and drew one to the taverne that had vowed not to drinke wine, and mingled wine and beere and drew him to drinke it, and then clapt him on the ſhoulder and bad him make vowes no more, for he had now broken it; and did preach openly, <hi>That to preach nothing but Scripture without authority of the Fathers, was like the devils ſheering of hoggs, a great cry, but a litle wooll.</hi> And ſaid upon the diſſolution of the late Parliament, that the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of that Parliament were a company of logger headed fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes.</p>
            <p n="88">88. The Benefice of <hi>Richard Goffe,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>East-Greenſteed</hi> in the county of <hi>Suſsex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common haunter of Tavernes and Ale-houſes, a common ſwearer of bloudy oathes, and ſinger of baudy ſongs and often drunke, and keepeth company with Papiſts and ſcandalous perſons, and hath confeſſed, <hi>That he chiefly ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died Popiſh Authours,</hi> highly commended Queene <hi>Maries</hi> time, and diſparaged Queene <hi>Elizabeths,</hi> as an enemy to learning, and hoped to ſee the time againe that there ſhould be no Bible in mens houſes. And hath openly preached, <hi>That ſuch as goe to other Pariſh Churches then their owne, are in the ſtate of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that after the bread and wine at the Sacrament is conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated, it is no more bread and wine, but the body and blood of Chriſt.</hi> And in a funerall Sermon at the buriall of a woman, ſaid, <hi>That ſhe being regenerated in Baptiſme did live and die without ſin:</hi> and hath expreſſed great malignancy againſt the Parliament, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That he hoped to ſee it confounded, and that he cared not a figg for the Parliament.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:112727:27"/>
            <p n="89">89. The Benefice of <hi>Thomas Staple,</hi> Vicar of the pariſh Church of <hi>Mundon</hi> in the county of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common frequenter of Tavernes and Ale-houſes, and a great drinker, and companion with drunken, debauſhed and malignant perſons: And upon the firſt of June in this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant yeare, 1643. being the next day after the Faſt, invited to his houſe a riotous company, to keepe a day of prophaneneſſe by drinking of healths round about a joyn'd-ſtoole, ſinging of prophane ſongs with hollowing and roaring, and at the ſame time enforced ſuch as came to him upon other occaſions, to drinke healths about the ſtoole with him, untill they were drunke. And hath taught, <hi>That it is not for Lay-men to meddle with the Word, nor yet to ſearch the Scriptures.</hi> And hath oft left his pariſhioners deſtitute of preaching on the Lords-day, even within theſe 12. moneths, and when he hath been abſent from them, hath ſubſtituted in his roome very drunken and debau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed Curates, and hath profeſſed, that if any of his pariſh that did not like of his courſe of life ſhould be ſicke, and ſend for him to be reconciled to him, hee would not come at him, though hee were ſure to ſave his ſoule thereby. And hath taught, <hi>That children dying without Baptiſme are all damned, and if any Infant that received the Sacrament of Baptiſme ſhould bee damned, he would be damned for him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="90">90. The Benefice of <hi>Peter Allen,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Tolſbury</hi> in the county of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he hath lived incontinently a long time with ſeverall women, that is to ſay with <hi>Mary Tim,</hi> who went from his houſe with child by him, <hi>Frances Smith,</hi> by whom he alſo had a baſtard. And with <hi>Ann Cooper</hi> whom he hath kept for the ſpace of 7 yeers laſt paſt, and yet keepeth in his houſe, who miſcarried of a child begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by him. And while the Railes were ſtanding about the Communion Table, he refuſed to adminiſter the Sacrament to ſuch as would not come to them. And hath beene very negligent of his Cure, abſenting himſelfe without any care ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for ſupply thereof a month together, whereby the bodies
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:112727:28"/>of the dead have beene left unburied ſeverall daies, and hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed great malignancy againſt the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="91">91. The Benefice of <hi>Iohn Hurt,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Horndon</hi> upon the hill, in the county of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common frequenter of Tavernes and Ale-houſes, and a common drunkard and gameſter, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſwearer and curſer, and hath beene convicted before the Juſtice of peace for ſix oathes at a time, and then ſware <hi>by God,</hi> he did not ſweare, and hath a very evill report of uncleanneſſe and abuſe of women, and hath ſpoken baſely of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and expreſſed malignancy againſt the ſame, and taught his Pariſhioners on Faſt-dayes in the after-noone to follow their worldly occaſions, and uſed himſelfe then to ſpend that time in the Ale-houſe.</p>
            <p n="92">92. The Benefices of <hi>Paul Clapham,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Farnham</hi> in the County of <hi>Surry</hi> and Parſon of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Martin Worthy</hi> in the county of <hi>South-hamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> are ſequeſtred, for that he hath lived in adultery with ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall women, and hath had divers baſtards and charged the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh with the keeping of them, and hath two baſtards at this time kept, one of which he payeth for the maintenance of, and is bound with his ſon to pay for the maintenance of the other. And hath called the Parliament and their adherents, Rebels and Traitours, and exhorted men to contribute and take up Armes againſt the Parliament, and hath deſerted his ſaid Cure and betaken himſelfe to the Army of Cavaleers about January laſt.</p>
            <p n="93">93. The Benefice of <hi>Iohn Amnes,</hi> Parſon of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Charleton</hi> in the County of <hi>Kent,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common drunkard, and hath beene drunke on the Faſt-daies, and uſeth to drinke healths, and in them to wiſh, <hi>That he might be curſed by Father, Mother and all his Kin, that endeth one health and will not another begin;</hi> And hath kept a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Ale-houſe, and is a prophaner of the Sabbath day, by common ſequenting of Ale-houſes thereon, and is a practiſer
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:112727:28"/>of the late Innovations, and would never preach himſelfe, nor ſuffer others to preach on the Sabbath-dayes in the after-noon, and hath attempted the chaſtity of divers women, and uſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſt behaviour towards them.</p>
            <p n="94">94. The Benefice of <hi>Robert Shepard,</hi> 
               <gap reason="blank" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Hepworth</hi> in the county of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common drunkard, and frequenter of Tavernes and Ale-houſes, lying and continuing drunke in the ſaid houſes di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers nights, ſometimes twice or thrice a weeke, and is greatly ſuſpected of incontinency, having had divers maid-ſervants depart from his houſe great with child, none living in the houſe with them but himſelfe, and ſome of them have returned againe to live with him, and within a ſhort time have been with-child againe; And hath been a great practiſer of the Altar-worſhip, an inforcer of his Pariſhioners to receive the Sacrament at the railes, and hath put 15. at a time from the Sacrament for refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to receive it at the railes; And in his Catechiſing and prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, calls his pariſhioners, <hi>Black-mouthed hell-hounds, Limmes of the Devill, Fire-brands of Hell, Plow joggers, Bawling doggs, Weaverly Iacks, and Church-Robbers,</hi> affirming, <hi>that if he could terme them worſe he would;</hi> And hath endeavoured to perſwade poore men to forſweare themſelves for him, and hath affirmed, <hi>That the Parliament were but a company of factious ſpirits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="95">95. The Benefice of <hi>Iohn Woolhouſe,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>West-Merſea</hi> in the county of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common and exceſſive tipler and drinker both at home and abroad, a common Ale-houſe haunter and drunkard, and on the Lords day going from the Church to the Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe in the fore-noon, and continuing tipling there till the after-noon ſervice, and uſeth to intice and provoke others to joyne in the ſame exceſſe with him, even to drunkenneſſe, and is a common dicer and gameſter for money, inticing his tipling companions thereunto, and is a common curſer and ſwearer, and hath tempted women to incontinency, and hath expreſſed great malignancy againſt the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:112727:29"/>
            <p n="96">96. The Benefice of <hi>Henry Hannington,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Hougham</hi> in the county of <hi>Kent,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common and notorious drunkard, and oft lying dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drunke in high-wayes, and hath continued ſo for the ſpace of twenty yeares and upwards, and uſeth to ſing in his cupps in the Ale-houſe baudy ſongs, which he calleth <hi>Cathedrall Songs,</hi> and on <hi>Eaſter</hi>-Eve and the ſeverall Saturdayes before and after that, he was ſo drunke that he was ſcarce able to ſpeake, and yet did adminiſter the Communion on the three Sundayes follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them; And being likely to recover the <hi>Peere</hi> of <hi>Dover</hi> to be within the bounds of his Pariſh, hee was asked how ſo great a number could have roome in ſo ſmall a Church as his, and his anſwer was, <hi>Let them pay me their offerings at</hi> Eaſter, <hi>and let them all goe to the Devill at</hi> Whitſontide, and hath been ſo negligent of his Cure, as children have been ſix or ſeven weekes unbaptized, and the reſt of the pariſh wholy neglected; And when he read the Book of Sports on the Lords day, there was Beere laid into his Barne, and dancing and drinking there that day, and to give them the more time for it, he diſmiſſed the Congregation with a few prayers, and left off preaching in the after-noone; And was at the time of the late Innovations, a very forward promotor, and diligent practiſer of them, and threatned the Church-wardens when they took downe the communion-Table into the Church, and when young people and ſervants have come to him to pay their offerings and be examined of their fitneſſe to receive the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, his manner alwayes was, to aske them, <hi>How many Piggs their Fathers and Maſters had, and how many Fowle they kept, and how many Lambes,</hi> and when they had fully informed him thereof, admitted them to the Sacrament without any further exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p n="97">97. The Benefice of <hi>Samuel Sowthen,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Malendine</hi> in the county of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he is a common haunter of Ale-houſes and Tavernes, and often drunke even upon the Lords day, and is a common pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voker
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:112727:29"/>of others to drinke exceſſively, rejoycing when he had made them drunke; and is a common ſwearer and curſer, and hath refuſed to deliver the Sacrament of the Lords Supper to his pariſhioners that would not come to the railes to receive, and uſeth to bow to the Elements in the Sacrament, lifting them up and imbracing them, and hath adminiſtred the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lords Supper in one kind only, and preached in maintenance thereof, and hath been a diligent practiſer of the late Innovations, and perſwader of others thereunto, and hath frequently enveighed againſt painfull Preachers and their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, comparing them to <hi>Pedlers</hi> and <hi>Ballad-ſingers, that have moſt company, when rich Merchants have but few,</hi> and hath perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted his Pariſhioners even to excommunication, for going to heare Sermons at other Churches on the Lords-day in the after-noone, when they had none at home, and hath expreſſed great malignity againſt the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and is vehemently ſuſpected of living incontinently, and in adultery with <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine Hayward,</hi> and hath been ſeverall times preſented to the Eccleſiaſticall Court by the Church-wardens and ſides-men for the ſame.</p>
            <p n="98">98. The Benefice of <hi>Thomas Heard,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>West-Tukely</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is ſepueſtred, for that he is a common drunkard and companion of drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, and hath been ſo drunke, that he hath tumbled into dit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and mire, and hath been oft drunke ſince he was complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of in Parliament, and in one of his drunken fitts, called for a fire to be made, and vowed he would burne his Wife and children in it, and refuſed to deliver the Sacrament to his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhioners for not kneeling at the ledge of the railes, though they did preſent themſelves kneeling neere unto it within his reach, and when the former Parliament brake up, ſaid boaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>That he hoped then to live to ſee all the Puritans hanged.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="99">99. The Benefice of <hi>Samuel Scrivener,</hi> Parſon of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Westhropp</hi> in the County of <hi>Suffolk,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he did frequently bow towards the communion-Table,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:112727:30"/>affirming, <hi>That there was an inherent holineſse in that place,</hi> and hath committed adultery with <hi>Margaret</hi> the Wife of <hi>George Woods,</hi> and is a common frequenter of Ale-houſes, and hath been often drunke, and hath ſaid, <hi>That the County of</hi> Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk <hi>had choſen ſuch factious fellowes for their Knights, that the Parliament was not like to hold,</hi> and hath preached againſt this preſent defenſive war of the Parliament and Kingdome.</p>
            <p n="100">100. The Benefice of <hi>Ambroſe Weſtrop,</hi> Vicar of the Pariſh Church of <hi>Much-Totham</hi> in the Countie of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> is ſequeſtred, for that he doth commonly prophane the ordinance of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, by venting in the Pulpit, matters concerning the ſecrets of Women, to ſtir up his auditory to laughter; And hath taught in his Sermons, <hi>That a man that uſeth carnall copulation with his wife the night before the adminiſtration of the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, unleſse his wife require him ſo to doe, ought not to come to the Sacrament of the Lords Supper; and that a woman that hath Monethly ſickneſſe, ought not to come to the Sacrament; That a Woman is worſe then a Sow, in two reſpects;</hi> Firſt, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe a Sowes skinne is good to make a Cart-ſaddle, and her Bristles good for a Sowter.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Becauſe a Sow will runne away if a man cry but</hi> Hoy, <hi>but a woman will not turne head, though beaten downe with a Leaver; and that all the difference betweene a Woman and a Sow, is in the nape of the neck, where a Woman can bend upwards, but the Sow cannot, and that a woman is reſpected by a man, onely for his uncleane luſt, and that ſhe that is nurſed with Sowes milke, will learne to wallow;</hi> and divers modeſt women abſenting from Church, becauſe of ſuch uncivill paſſages, he affirmed, <hi>That all that were then abſent from Church were whores:</hi> And having been a ſutor to a Widdow whom he called <hi>Black Beſſe,</hi> who rejected him and married another, he obſerved in his Sermon out of one of the <hi>Pſalmes, That</hi> David <hi>prayed to God, not to Saint or An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell, nor yet to black Beſſe,</hi> who was then in the Church before him; <hi>and that</hi> Jacob <hi>to deceive his brother of the bleſsing, made lie upon lie, but when</hi> Eſau <hi>came home and perceived it, he flung a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with a pox,</hi> and ſpeaking againſt ſuch as pleaſed him not in
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:112727:30"/>paying the tithes, in the Pulpit he turned toward his brother in-law then in the Church, and ſaid, <hi>You brother Block-head will pay no tithe-Buſhes neither,</hi> And being angry with one whoſe name was <hi>Kent,</hi> he ſaid thus in the Pulpit, <hi>they ſay the Devill is in</hi> Harwich, <hi>but I am ſure he is in</hi> Kent; And ſpeaking of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of thoſe that made excuſes for not coming to the marriage, he obſerved, <hi>That the married man had no excuſe,</hi> but ſaid in plaine termes, <hi>he could not come,</hi> Nay ſaid he, <hi>the married man cannot come, but muſt goe to Hell in his whore:</hi> And at another time told a ſtory in the Pulpit of two ſeverall women, that in their husbands abſence had familiars, and ſaid, <hi>that when it was night they went up into the chamber together with a candle, and put out the candle, and there is ſport, heavenly ſport, ſuch ſport as never was in lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Heaven;</hi> and when their husbands come home, they muſt enquire the way by Horne-row, <hi>and that</hi> Rahab <hi>was a whore, and kept an Ale-houſe at</hi> Jericho, <hi>and that ſo are all Ale-wives whores and their husbands Cuckoulds;</hi> And being a ſutor to one Miſtris <hi>Ellen Pratt</hi> a Widdow, he did write upon a peece of paper theſe words, <hi>Bonny Nell, I love thee well,</hi> and did pin it on his cloake, and ware it up and downe a Market-Towne, which wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man refuſing him, he did for five or ſix weekes after, utter little or nothing elſe in the Pulpit, but invectives againſt Women; And being ſutor to another woman, who failed to come to din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner upon invitation to his houſe, he immediately roade to her houſe, and deſiring to ſpeake with her, ſhe coming to the doore, without ſpeaking to her, he pulled off her head-geere and rode away with it, and many other like paſſages fall from him in his preaching, and were proved againſt him.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
